<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COMM-260 Quant Methods &amp; Data Viz (Fall 2018)</title>
    <description>Final projects from students in Quantitative Methods &amp; Data Visualization at American University Spring 2018.  
</description>
    <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 11:11:11 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 11:11:11 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Treble in Paradise is searching for an audience, not Instagram likes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Treble in Paradise is American University’s oldest all-female a cappella group. Established in 2004, Treble in Paradise is currently comprised of fifteen girls who perform wearing their signature pink high heels. The group has a substantial following among American University students as well as the larger D.C. community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At AU in general, it’s hard to get people excited about activities like sports and music,” said music director Maegan Weinhold. “The people in our audience, it’s always peoples best friends or a frat that is close to the girls.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://trebleinparadise.wixsite.com/treble&quot;&gt;Treble in Paradise&lt;/a&gt; has performed at baseball games for the Washington Nationals, three consecutive National Christmas Tree Lightings as well as the nationally televised National Cherry Blossom Festival. Despite the group’s ever-growing follower pool, there seems to be a disconnect between Treble in Paradise’s social media and their concert attendance rate. “In general it has always been people who swim in our circle - relatives, friends, potential auditionees, members from other a cappella groups. But this is not effective,” Weinhold said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The male counterpart to Treble is On a Sensual Note (OASN), AU’s only all-male a cappella group. While the members of their respective fan bases differ, their concert attendance rates are strikingly similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/concertinvites.png&quot; alt=&quot;concertinvites.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/concertattendance.png&quot; alt=&quot;concertattendence.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OASN invited 732 people to their winter concert through their Facebook event page for the November 30th event. Of those 732, there were approximately 250 people in the audience. Treble invited 359 people through their Facebook event, and approximately 125 of them showed up to the Kay Spiritual Life Center for the gig on Dec 1. Both groups had roughly a 34 percent attendance rate for their concerts - Treble’s 34.8 percent was slightly higher than OASN’s 34.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treble’s following on social media platforms like Facebook and Instagram has shown popularity among their targeted demographic: college students. The vast majority of Treble’s Instagram followers are women between the ages of 18-24 based in Washington, D.C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/instagender.png&quot; alt=&quot;instagender.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/instagramages.png&quot; alt=&quot;instagramages.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treble’s Public Relations Chair and AU sophomore, Josee Molavi, is working to make a change in the group’s following pool. Molavi pointed out that social media is constantly changing, and Instagram in particular can now be used as the primary marketing tool for university clubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growing popularity of Instagram “Stories” has also become a tool of which Molavi says she is trying to take full advantage. She can post pictures, videos and links to Treble’s YouTube on their Instagram Story and then track the number of “impressions” the post has made throughout the day. Instagram allows users like Treble, who have business profiles, to track the number of profile visits, link clicks and emails sent through the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/interactions.png&quot; alt=&quot;interactions.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Molavi, follower count is more about quality than quantity. She says the crucial step in gaining a more engaged following was actually unfollowing some accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said, “Our following was never significantly engaged in the past. In terms of us following people back who come to our gigs, that was kind of outdated. I unfollowed a lot of people, and then followed a lot more people that were actually engaging in our content, which makes for a better community of people to share our content with.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems as though these changes have yet to manifest in a larger turnout at concerts. Weinhold is aware of the disconnect and chalks it up to the groups differing fan bases and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said, “I’ve noticed that On a Sensual Note’s campus fanbase is larger, but they have no well-known presence in the larger DC area, and their social media following is same. Our two groups are the same on all fronts, but we have a greater DC presence and they have a greater campus presence.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem is not a uniquely AU one, according to Joy Owings, a member of the co-ed &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebeltones.squarespace.com&quot;&gt;Belmont University Beltones&lt;/a&gt;. She said that the Beltones sometimes have difficulty drawing a crowd, but that she thinks the group’s prominence in Nashville, often nicknamed “Music City”, has a lot to do with their exposure and ability to reach a wider fanbase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked about the Beltones’ following she said, “It grew when we were in ICCAs two years ago, significantly dropped last year because all we did was record for an album. I think the Beltones has a higher concert attendance just because we’re in Nashville and music is everywhere. The music environment just isn’t the same in D.C.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race to gain more followers never ends for collegiate a cappella groups. Weinhold spoke the Treble in Paradise’s growing success and how that has translated into the group’s growing popularity and following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The group became ‘good’ when we started to get cool gigs like singing at Nats games, Caps games and auditioning for The Sing Off,” she said, “From those gigs, those tangible accomplishments gave us something to post about that set us apart and showed our followers our credibility.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Former OASN President Peter Close said, “Overall, we’ve seen a decrease in the average attendance of our concerts. From what I’ve been told, all the groups on campus had their peak around the time the first Pitch Perfect movie came out.” He also said that much of the group’s publicity comes from individual members rather than the official OASN accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps group member engagement is the key to audience engagement, both on and offline.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/treble/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/treble/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding and Combating Sexual Violence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a core lack of understanding when it comes to themes of sexual violence and sexual assault, and it stems from the fact that we as society have backdoored sex into something that isn’t supposed to be discussed, and therefore leads to a lack of necessary discussions when it comes to topics involving sex which includes Sexual Assault. We do the women in our society, who are the obvious victims, and men the not so obvious victims, of sexual violence a disservice when we refuse to educate ourselves on these topics, and choose to remain ignorant. The purpose of this article is not to pull on heartstrings, but rather to encourage those who have convinced themselves that sexual violence, harassment, or misconduct is something that only happens to a select group of people, or in the unfortunate instance with the #Metoo movement, women just lying for fame. There is a bigger conversation that needs to be had about how sex is treated in this country and how that plays into why Americans do not take instances of sexual misconduct seriously, but that is an article for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assist me with this article I sought the help of American Universities Offices of Advocacy Services for Interpersonal and Sexual Violence (OASIS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding&quot;&gt;Understanding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began my research into this topic, by conducting a survey in which I aimed to gauge at what level people understood, and interacted with sexual assault and misconduct. The survey was broken up into three sections. The first section attempted to interact with those who have been victims of sexual assault. The second part was a look into how sexual misconduct appeared in their everyday lives, and the last section attempted to see if people understood commonly used terms when it comes to sexual assault. There are many terms involved in the unpacking of sexual misconduct. Corrosion, consent, exploitation, harassment, and the list goes on, but I choose to test on the basic terminology that people in the field of sexaul misconduct use, and the ones that in an ideological world everyone would know what they meant. I asked for the definitions of Rape, Consent, Sexual Harassment, Sexual Assault, and Sexual Misconduct. Out of 120 people only 108 people attempted to define rape and only about 25%  understood what Rape is actually categorized as. 107 people attempted to define consent 100% o those who answered had the basic understanding. But as we unpack later. At the basis of consent, yes, it is an agreement a yes or no to continue on with a specific activity, but there is more to it. 104 people attempted to define Sexual Assault and only about 25% got it right. Sexual Assault is an umbrella term for ANY sexual activity that was not consented to. It does not have to be forceful, groping, and rape are all under this term. Simply smacking someone on the ass is sexual assault. Sexual Harassment had 102 responses, closer to 100% got this right. Sexual Harassment is unwanted vermal and not physical sexual advancement, we usually see this in the workplace, and this was a lot of what Harvey Weinstein was being accused of. Sexual Harassment can be continued sexual advances, even if you are not touching the person. 97 people attempted to define Sexual Misconduct, which trips people up because of how close in definition it is to sexual assault. But what is important to remember that while Assault has to do with physical contact, misconduct encompases everything. From simply telling someone nice ass, catcalling, all the way to forced unwanted touching. People had a tougher time with this definition, less than 25 actually got the definition correct. This shows a big problem, while 120 people is not a valid representation of the American population it still says a lot that most people cannot differentiate, the difference between on and the other. A lot of the responders equated force, and violence to a lot of these terms, which explains why people get themselves into certain situations and lack the realization that what they were doing is legally, and morally wrong. The lack of understanding is what leads people to view sexual assault in the light they do is because they do not understand. When Bill Cosby was sentenced to prison, members of the Black community, questioned why Cosby was sentenced but other were not. Cosby was found guilty of rape, while other were only accused of sexual misconduct, and because we do not understand we group them all as the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;consent&quot;&gt;Consent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have chosen to dedicate a miniature section to consent because as much as the topic has been in public light most people still do not understand what consent is. For example taking the condom off during sex is rape if I did not agree to have sex with you, without a condom. As a sexually active college student, I have had encounters which have almost bordered on misconduct and even almost assault because most of the men I have had as partners have lacked the basic understanding of what is and what is not appropriate. I have had friends express to me, multiple times when they have been forced to either orally pleasure a male partner because they corosed them into doing it by refusing to take no for an answer. Or male partners who have moved their hand onto their genitalia. These stories are not isolated, and they happen quite often. My first time, my partner did not take into the fact that I was telling him no and to e careful because of the pain I was in. Instead he kept going until he was done Now I do not consider myself a victim, but in an alternate world someone else could have been scared by that even, and when we were the done the look on his face made it clear that he did not think he had done anything wrong. When the Aziz Ansari story broke men jumped to defend him because they saw themselves in that Narrative, because they too have done that to women. So what is consent then? If I tell you no, you must stop even if we have already began being intimate with each other. Consent isn’t pushing the topic until I say yes. Men and women when engaging in sexual activity must clearly make sure that their partner is ok with EVERYTHING that is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impact&quot;&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual Assault Impacts us all on a daily basis, most women interact with different forms of sexaul misconduct on a daily basis, and most people have been victims of sexual assault. When I was in preschool I had boys put their hands down my pants in the middle of class. As a kid it made me uncomfortable, and I did not understand what was happening, and to be honest I do not believe those boys themselves understood what was happening either. In middle school the boys in my class would make a habit of smacking girls on their bottoms, or making comments about breast sizes. As kids we don’t see the problem with this, we laugh it off and call it boys being boys. As a college aged woman, I have been groped at parties, had male genitalia rubbed on me from behind, and pulled without my consent. I have stared at and cat called from cars on my way to class. Sexual harassment has been a part of my story, and the stories of so many others, but we do not acknowledge it because we turn a blind eye. We must begin to become frank about these issues, and I like so many other women even though we have been victims, do not perceive ourselves as victims because we have become desensitized to it. In my survey I asked how many people had been victims of sexual assault, and out of 121 responders about 68% said yes to being victims. What was interesting is that there were people who put no, but only did so because they did not know i their experience could be defined as assault or not. We’re so focused on the belief that assault is forced or violent, that everyday misconduct goes unnoticed, and victims are left questioning if they are actually victims. Out of those who said they were assaulted only about 14% actually reported it and out of that 14% only 15% of the perpetrators were actually punished. I asked people how many women they knew were victims of sexual assault about 40% said they knew about 1-5 women who were assaulted, and about 45% said they knew from about 1-5 men who had been victims. Sexual Assault Impacts us more than we realize. For those who had been victims I asked when the assault happened about 31% said during college. This pushed me to seek out more information from American Universities OASIS, who gave me some numbers, and a new perspective through the conversation we had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/victim1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/victim2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/victim3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-university-report-data&quot;&gt;American University Report Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/180123&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/180125&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that these numbers are only a representation of those who choose to report, and that a majority of people choose not to report the fact that they were in fact victims, because of facts of shame and fear of retaliation, and even the very real possibility that people will not believe them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;false-claim&quot;&gt;False Claim&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my interview with OASIS they noted that fall semester of 2018, they have seen a drop in the number of clients they have, and hypothesized that this may have been a result of the kavanaugh hearings and the fear that when coming forward with their stories. False claim is not as high as you would think it is. Only about 2-8% percent of rape are actually false claim accusations. Sara Yzaguirre who is the coordinator for victim advocacy services, noted that her seven years in this line of work she’s worked with maybe a thousand victims, and not once can she remember one actually attempting to falsely accuse someone. The process of actually accusing someone and the mental toll it takes on someone why would anyone put themselves through that? So why do we buy into the narrative of False Claims? Maya Vizvary, the sexual assault prevention coordinator notes that it might have to do with the fact that the sexual assault stories we often hear are high profile cases. It’s the powerful men we hear about, and think that these women are only accusing these men because they want something “she must want money, she must want fame.” Because of this we prescribe the same thinking to the other stories we hear involving assault. In my survey when I asked how many personal false claim stories people have heard 73 percent said 0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/victim4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;combating-sexual-assault&quot;&gt;Combating Sexual Assault&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combating Sexual assault starts with having open conversations, but also addressing issues that we have not addressed before. The first thing we need to know is that rape, and assault are not based in sex, but rather in power. That is why as Ms. Yzaguirre note that 90% of perpetrators are men regardless of if the victim is male or female, and marginalized groups have higher rates of sexual victimization. People commit rape, not because they are sexual deviants that cannot control themselves, but they do it because they can. We combat this issue by actually acknowledging that sexual assault claims are not just from slutty college girls, who got their feeling hurt after the star football player didn’t want to date her after she had sex with him. There is more, we need to denormalize how we view sexual assault. The media plays into this, porn feeds into this, and as a society we internalize and go along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/victim5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/victim6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/sexual-assault/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/sexual-assault/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Has immigration to the U.S. changed over time?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The misconceptions about Latin American asylum seekers versus international refugees&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON - Over the past few years, the United States has noticed many changes in immigration from countries worldwide. Data shows that these changes can be a result of many factors, but the perceptions in the United States of certain immigrant stereotypes have a single narrative: a Spanish-speaking individual or family, illegally crossing the border, and embedding themselves into the American workforce. But in 2016 when Donald Trump was elected President of the United States, a strict and, at times &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/trump-attacks-protections-for-immigrants-from-shithole-countries-in-oval-office-meeting/2018/01/11/bfc0725c-f711-11e7-91af-31ac729add94_story.html?utm_term=.93b4d4a0dcb9&quot;&gt;aggressive&lt;/a&gt;, immigration policy emerged. However, the numbers show that Latin America/Caribbean immigration to the U.S. has steadily declined whereas African immigration has almost doubled since 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. was founded as a country of immigrants but the first big wave of immigration in U.S. history can be seen in early 1900. However, the reaction to this was heavy restrictions on immigration in the 1920s. It wasn’t until loosened rules in the 1960s permitted the current wave made up mostly of Latin Americans and Asians. Today, claims in mass media and statements from Donald Trump focus on the U.S. being overwhelmed by immigrants from Mexico and the rest of Latin America, encouraging the government to build a wall across the southern border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Immigrants are always different. As a country of immigrants, other than the Native Americans, there have always been immigrants going in waves based on what’s going in their home countries,” Susanna Campbell, a former member on the Council on Foreign Relations and UNICEF Burundi, said. “So the wave to immigrants in this country has been different every decade or so. In fact, that’s how you could trace the evolution of the policy shifts in the U.S. with the question of who was immigrating at that point in time and what time of policies were in consideration to them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/newsroom/blogs/random-samplings/2017/03/immigrant_familiesa.html&quot;&gt;U.S. Census Bureau’s American Community Survey’s&lt;/a&gt;  numbers show that immigration from Latin America is slowing, as recent arrivals are coming from countries in Asia and are more prone than native-born Americans to obtain a college education. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/the-avenue/2018/09/24/21st-century-immigration-favors-asians-and-college-grads-as-the-us-foreign-born-share-rises/&quot;&gt;“21st-century immigrants”&lt;/a&gt;  are locating in parts of the country where immigrant concentration has been low, and in many states that supported Trump in the 2016 election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Academically I see them as a demographic group that needs a lot of assistance where they are true asylum seekers they deserve due process,” said Bill Belding, a professional lecturer and expert on warfare and counterinsurgency operations. “But I just go back or forth on that issue. I’m from California so immigrants there is a significant part of the economy. So I think if they are able to contribute to the economy and pay their taxes, I think they should be able to be here.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-0HYWF&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/0HYWF/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;0HYWF&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;0HYWF&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:525,&quot;200&quot;:450,&quot;300&quot;:425,&quot;400&quot;:425,&quot;500&quot;:400,&quot;700&quot;:400,&quot;800&quot;:400,&quot;900&quot;:400,&quot;1000&quot;:400},window.datawrapper[&quot;0HYWF&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-0HYWF&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;0HYWF&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;0HYWF&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;0HYWF&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;0HYWF&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;0HYWF&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tazreena Sajjad, a professorial lecturer in the School of International Service (SIS) at American University in Washington D.C. specializes in transitional justice with refugees and forced displacement. She said that the conversation of refugees fleeing and coming to the United States is part of a much broader conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sajjad notes that the differences between labeling refugees, immigrants, and asylum seekers are very important in this broader discussion. But the biggest distinction, according to Sajjad, is the discrepancies in the United States’ resettlement program for refugees entering the country. This process includes analysis from The Departments of Homeland Security and State and Health and Human Services through the U.S. Resettlement Program that was put in place with the creation and passing of the United States Refugee Act of 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The community that enters the United States fleeing conflict, violence, climate change, so on and so forth, they are what would be asylum seekers and largely they come from Central America because the United States does not have a resettlement program for Central America,” Sajjad said. “So people actually have to enter the United States and ask the United States government to review their individual cases, to determine whether they can be classified as a refugee or not.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the nation’s foreign-born share continues to rise, recent immigration looks different now than that which characterized much of the late 20th century. This important change is with immigrants’ country of origin. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/the-avenue/2018/09/24/21st-century-immigration-favors-asians-and-college-grads-as-the-us-foreign-born-share-rises/&quot;&gt;William H. Frey’s analysis of 2017 American Community Survey&lt;/a&gt;, Asia now exceeds Latin America as the major origin region for foreign-born residents that have arrived since 2010. In the same token, most people do not know that about one-quarter of the population age 25 and older are either foreign-born or have at least one foreign-born parent, according to the U.S. Census Bureau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;371&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vSKRDnxj9BgEMn3yWLr-2NjvS4CaEpUSXC_5tykFc5g1PvwobFyB4lncT5ov_Q6dT1PGZn9rAMmvqMy/pubchart?oid=139519658&amp;amp;format=interactive&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“States with high immigration populations also get high asylum seekers,” said Anne Schaufele, a practitioner-in-residence with the International Human Rights Law Clinic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schaufele, reaffirming Sajjad’s points, said that the differences between asylum seekers and immigrants are the asylum seekers are primarily coming from the Mexico-US border to California, Texas, or Arizona. To focus on the differences is to understand that many refugees come from the Middle East or Africa whereas most asylum seekers come from Central America.
The anecdote of the Spanish-speaking immigrant fleeing their country for prosperity in the United States is not an unfamiliar story. But Campbell said the insinuation that now there are more perceived illegal immigrants than prior revolves around the narrative that immigration boils down to being illegal or legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With consecutive waves of immigrants, there’s a narrative around why they are coming and what makes them different so today it’s illegal/legal but whether that’s fundamentally different that historically depends on who you ask,” Campbell said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, African immigration has been roughly doubling every decade since 1970, according to a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/the-avenue/2018/09/24/21st-century-immigration-favors-asians-and-college-grads-as-the-us-foreign-born-share-rises/&quot;&gt;Pew Research Center analysis of U.S. Census Bureau data.  According to the 2018 report to Congress&lt;/a&gt;, there are currently over 5.6 million refugees across the African continent, constituting over 30 percent of the global refugee population. Refugee numbers in Africa increased by 1.5 million since 2015 due to new or intensified conflicts across the continent. Ongoing conflicts in three countries – Burundi, Nigeria, and South Sudan – are primarily responsible for the growth in refugee numbers in 2016 and 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/179874&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are many refugees coming from the Middle East and African countries that are riddled with conflict and violence,” said Ana Corina Alonso-Yoder, a practitioner-in-residence with the Immigrant Justice Clinic. “Countries like Syria and Yemen, which go through process slightly different than asylum seekers since the second group are people generally most represented by the Central American Region.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the southern borders embedding many of the Central American asylum seekers into their economies, Alonso-Yoder said that it’s difficult for average Americans to get past the cliches of immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the immigrant population in the U.S. continues to evolve, American policies respond to these changing tides while the misconceptions surrounding immigration continue to grow. As this administration continues the tirade against the stereotypical 21st-century immigrant, data shows it’s not as clearcut as it may seem.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/immigration/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/immigration/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stanley Cup parties and avoiding their hangovers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For the Washington Capitals’ 44-year existence, the team had failed to win the Stanley Cup, hockey’s most coveted trophy. They had only advanced to the finals once and lost in a clean sweep of the series. This franchise knew heartbreak, and fans were tired of cheering for a team that always let them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It almost makes you want to stop cheering for them,” said Emily Minton, a Northern Virginia native and longtime season ticket holder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those years of heartbreak washed away on June 7, 2018, when the game clock struck zero in Game 5 of the Stanley Cup finals and the Washington Capitals beat the Vegas Golden Knights. The Caps were crowned the champions for the first time in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I felt like a huge weight had been lifted off my shoulders. It was like a relief that all my time spent watching them and cheering hadn’t been for nothing,” said Minton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the 2018-2019 season is underway after a summer frequently documented drunken celebrations, and many fans dread the Stanley Cup hangover. A Stanley Cup hangover is when, after winning the championship the previous season, a team has a noticeably worse season the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s such a hard thing,” Ken Hitchcock, Stanley Cup winning coach of the 1999 Dallas Stars, says to Sports Illustrated about avoiding the dreaded Cup hangover. “To ask players to repay the high price they paid is not as simple as the words say. You’re asking the players to do things that aren’t really very natural. You’ve really got to find a way for them to get re-engaged.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winning the Stanley Cup is challenging, but avoiding a Stanley Cup hangover is even more so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-stanley-cup-hangover&quot;&gt;What is a Stanley Cup hangover?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When attempting to determine whether or not the Stanley Cup hangover is real, a concrete definition of a hangover is necessary. A team that suffers from the Stanley Cup hangover will experience a decrease in performance, particularly among specific key stats. If a team meets seven of the following regressions, we will consider them to have had a hangover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-zjYf9&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/zjYf9/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;615&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;zjYf9&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;zjYf9&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:693,&quot;200&quot;:667,&quot;300&quot;:641,&quot;400&quot;:615,&quot;500&quot;:615,&quot;700&quot;:615,&quot;800&quot;:615,&quot;900&quot;:615,&quot;1000&quot;:615},window.datawrapper[&quot;zjYf9&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-zjYf9&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;zjYf9&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;zjYf9&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;zjYf9&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;zjYf9&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;zjYf9&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For determinants 5-15, the percentages which a hungover team drop below are the league medians over the years analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major decrease in team points is the most obvious sign of a hangover for a championship team. Though repeating as champions is extremely difficult, regular season success is expected to be similar to the previous year, the season when the Stanley Cup was won. The rest of the statistics measure a team’s success on the ice beyond wins and losses. The advanced metrics such as Corsi For Percentage and Scoring Chance Goals For Percentage measure a team’s efficiency on the ice and give a more in-depth look at how successful they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team that repeats as champions are automatically removed from consideration of having a hangover, as they were able to repeat the most difficult level of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, a team that does not meet seven of the above qualifications may still be considered to have a hangover if their regression in some of the categories was drastic enough to pull them down in other categories. Likewise, if a team meets seven or more of the qualifications but the regression is minimal, discretion will be taken when determining the validity of their hangover. These 15 qualifications serve as the guidelines for considering whether or not a team suffers from a hangover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2012 Kings championship and the 2013 Blackhawks championship are excluded from this narrative because the 2012-2013 NHL lockout, which lasted from Sept. 15, 2012 – Jan. 6, 2013. The shorter season provides incomplete data and therefore conclusions cannot be reliably drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at teams who have won over the past ten years, four were hungover and four escaped the hangover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Yh2gR&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Yh2gR/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;530&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;Yh2gR&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;Yh2gR&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:776,&quot;200&quot;:616,&quot;300&quot;:576,&quot;400&quot;:545,&quot;500&quot;:530,&quot;700&quot;:530,&quot;800&quot;:530,&quot;900&quot;:516,&quot;1000&quot;:516},window.datawrapper[&quot;Yh2gR&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-Yh2gR&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;Yh2gR&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;Yh2gR&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;Yh2gR&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;Yh2gR&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;Yh2gR&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;escaping-the-hangover&quot;&gt;Escaping the hangover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to draw conclusions regarding the possible Capitals hangover, past champions and their subsequent seasons must be considered. Of the last 10 years, four teams’ production remains consistent the year after a Stanley Cup victory. Specifically, the 2009-2010 Pittsburgh Penguins, 2011-2012 Boston Bruins, 2015-2016 Chicago Blackhawks, and 2016-2017 Pittsburgh Penguins all experienced similar or greater success the year after winning the Stanley Cup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the recurring presence of the Pittsburgh Penguins suggests a unique franchise stability, the high number of other teams who maintain their success suggests that the inevitability of a Stanley Cup Hangover is a myth. While teams certainly can suffer from a hangover, the success of many defending champions suggests that the Stanley Cup hangover is avoidable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in the case of the 2011-2012 Boston Bruins, the season after a championship can be a time for improvement. The Bruins experienced major boosts in all categories except for points (decrease of one percent), Scoring Chance Saves (decrease of two percent), and High Danger Saves (decrease of one percent), meaning they only fell short in one category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bruins did not play defense as well as during their championship season, as evidenced by save percentages decreasing. What they lacked in goalkeeping they certainly made up for in shooting, as they scored an extra 16 goals thanks to increases in all of the advanced offensive metrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2016-2017 Pittsburgh Penguins repeated as Stanley Cup Champions, proving they clearly did not suffer from a hangover, though a more in-depth look at the differences between championship teams makes it clear that the Penguins maintained excellence. They finished the regular season behind only the Washington Capitals with an incredible 111 points. Additionally, despite shooting less than 50 percent of the shots in a game, more than 50 percent of scoring chances resulted in goals. This means that the 2016-2017 Penguins were extremely efficient, generating only the best of scoring chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;falling-victim-to-the-hangover&quot;&gt;Falling victim to the hangover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some teams are able to avoid the dreaded hangover, others are not as lucky. The four teams which experienced what we classify as a Stanley Cup Hangover are the 2008-2009 Detroit Red Wings, the 2010-2011 Chicago Blackhawks, the 2014-2015 Los Angeles Kings, and the 2017-2018 Pittsburgh Penguins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008-2009 Detroit Red Wings were a team close to escaping a hangover with decreases in seven categories, which dropped just enough for us to notice. The 2014-2015 Los Angeles Kings did not significantly drop in more than three categories but failed to qualify for the Stanley Cup playoffs and were comparatively much worse than many other teams that season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010-2011 Chicago Blackhawks offer a look at the average hangover, a team who hit the seven minimum decreases in production to qualify as hungover. Most notably, there was a significant decrease in team points after the Hawks won the Cup. Because they lost 8 more games than the previous season with one extra overtime win, they ended the 2010-2011 season with 15 less points than the year prior. A major contributor to this poor record is their Goals For and Goals Against.  After winning the Cup, they scored 10 less goals but allowed 17 more than the year before. Both of these factors strongly indicate a hangover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the goals and team points, the team saw significant decreases in Corsi For, Scoring Chance For, High Danger Chance For, and High Danger Goals For, meaning their efficiency at generating and capitalizing on scoring opportunities fell.  While their power play percentage increased, their penalty kill percentage decreased to a greater extent, eliminating special teams’ progress. In fact, the power play production is the only statistics to significantly improve the season after the Blackhawks won the Cup. In fact, none of their statistics increased by more than one percent, and all of the others decreased by no more than two percent. By themselves, it is insignificant, but combined, it shows a lack of consistency and progress following their championship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-kujSS&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/kujSS/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;543&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;kujSS&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;kujSS&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:793,&quot;200&quot;:668,&quot;300&quot;:593,&quot;400&quot;:568,&quot;500&quot;:568,&quot;700&quot;:543,&quot;800&quot;:543,&quot;900&quot;:543,&quot;1000&quot;:518},window.datawrapper[&quot;kujSS&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-kujSS&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;kujSS&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;kujSS&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;kujSS&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;kujSS&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;kujSS&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On avoiding hangovers and replicating success of the past season, Peter Hassett, co-founder of the Washington Capitals fan blog, Russian Machine Never Breaks, stressed how difficult this can be: “The NHL has enough parity and randomness to make back-to-backs very hard to accomplish. One would have to be very, very lucky to do so – and then the hangover will come hard.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And boy, did the hangover come hard for the 2017-2018 Pittsburgh Penguins, a team coming off back-to-back championship seasons who subsequently fell far back in the standings. This team had the highest number of statistical regressions of any team we analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a 111-point performance in the 2016-2017 season, the Penguins dropped 11 points to finish with 100. Their high danger chances compared to their opponents decreased by two percent and their ability to convert shots into goals suffered all around, but especially with high danger opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2017-2018 Penguins had several large regressions as well. Their percentage of goals scored off of all chances in a game dropped by 11 percent and their percentage of goals off high danger opportunities in a game dropped by 10 percent, with both numbers dropping below 50 percent. This means that of all scoring opportunities in a game, the Penguins are converting on less than half of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-u5vSg&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/u5vSg/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;477&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;u5vSg&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;u5vSg&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:552,&quot;200&quot;:527,&quot;300&quot;:502,&quot;400&quot;:477,&quot;500&quot;:477,&quot;700&quot;:477,&quot;800&quot;:477,&quot;900&quot;:477,&quot;1000&quot;:477},window.datawrapper[&quot;u5vSg&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-u5vSg&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;u5vSg&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;u5vSg&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;u5vSg&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;u5vSg&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;u5vSg&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the Penguins Scoring Chance Save percentage and High Danger Save percentage experienced slight regressions of two percent, just enough to take note of, though this is not surprising as the Penguins lost their starting goaltender in the Las Vegas expansion draft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-washington-capitals&quot;&gt;The Washington Capitals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How have the Washington Capitals fared so far this season? Surprisingly well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-gL351&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/gL351/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;286&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;gL351&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;gL351&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:590,&quot;200&quot;:431,&quot;300&quot;:378,&quot;400&quot;:339,&quot;500&quot;:325,&quot;700&quot;:300,&quot;800&quot;:300,&quot;900&quot;:300,&quot;1000&quot;:286},window.datawrapper[&quot;gL351&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-gL351&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;gL351&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;gL351&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;gL351&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;gL351&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;gL351&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Capitals currently are atop the Metro Division, which represents success,” said Hassett.  “They have the highest shooting percentage in the league during 5-on-5 play, which suggests that at least one of those elusive “lucky” factors are still in their favor.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far in this season, there might be more than one lucky factor in their favor. The only statistic that has decreased enough to note is their High Danger Chances For, which went down by two percent. In fact, despite their chances being down, their High Danger Shots and High Danger Goals For are both significantly up, by five percent and three percent. This means that despite having fewer high danger opportunities than their opponents, their ability to convert the chances they do get into shots and goals has increased since last season, with their high danger shot chances ranked second in the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, for the last two seasons, the Caps have been scoring more than expected and allowing less goals than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-7GBZB&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/7GBZB/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;670&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;7GBZB&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;7GBZB&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:1021,&quot;200&quot;:801,&quot;300&quot;:748,&quot;400&quot;:709,&quot;500&quot;:670,&quot;700&quot;:670,&quot;800&quot;:670,&quot;900&quot;:670,&quot;1000&quot;:631},window.datawrapper[&quot;7GBZB&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-7GBZB&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;7GBZB&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;7GBZB&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;7GBZB&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;7GBZB&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;7GBZB&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the teams we examined, few have maintained or improved their numbers to the extent the Capitals have from one season to the next. This is also impressive for another reason: the offseason and injuries. During the summer, the Capitals traded back-up goaltender Philipp Grubauer to start for the Colorado Avalanche and faceoff specialist Jay Beagle signed a new contract with the Vancouver Canucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Capitals faceoff percentage has slightly suffered from this season to the last, new backup goaltender Pheonix Copley has been playing admirably, maintaining above average save percentages while starting goaltender Braden Holtby was out for several games with an upper body injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other key members of the Caps line-up have been injured as well, such as Brooks Orpik, a veteran defenseman who is missing a minimum of seven weeks following knee surgery, and T.J. Oshie and Evgeny Kuznetsov, two top 6 forwards who both suffered concussions in the Nov. 14 game against the Winnipeg Jets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s Tom Wilson, who missed the first 16 games of the season due to a suspension for an illegal hit during the preseason, and then suffered a concussion 11 games later. Wilson is on track to have a career season with 14 points since returning to the lineup. Center Nicklas Backstrom, who is 31 years old, is also on track to have a career season, with 34 points in 29 games. Lastly, Captain Alex Ovechkin is on track to score at least 60 goals this season, a feat that is virtually unheard of for players older than 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Most importantly, the team is winning games. Whether they’ll be able to repeat as champions is another matter, but that should not be the threshold for a hangover,” said Hassett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this analysis considered, it is easily concluded that the Washington Capitals are not having a Stanley Cup hangover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Numbers thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hockey-reference.com&quot;&gt;Hockey Reference&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naturalstattrick.com&quot;&gt;Natural Stat Trick&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.corsicahockey.com&quot;&gt;Corsica Hockey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glossary:
&lt;strong&gt;Goals For (GF)&lt;/strong&gt; - Count of Goals for that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goals Against (GA)&lt;/strong&gt; - Count of Goals against that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shots on Goal/60 (SOG/60)&lt;/strong&gt; - Rate of Shots for that team per 60 minutes of play&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record&lt;/strong&gt; - the number of games won, regulation lost, and overtime lost&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Points&lt;/strong&gt; - Two points are awarded for a win, 1 point is awarded for an overtime loss, and no points are awarded for regulation loss&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Faceoffs Won Percentage  (FOW%)&lt;/strong&gt; - The percentage of faceoffs won by that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Save Percentage (SV%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of shots against that team that were not goals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power play Percentage (PP%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of times a team successfully scores on a man advantage penalty&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Penalty Kill Percentage (PK%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of times a team a is able to prevent a team from scoring on a man advantage penalty&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corsi For  Percentage (CF%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of total shot attempts in games that team played that are for that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scoring Chances For Percentage (SCF%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of total Scoring Chances in games that team played that are for that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Danger Chances For Percentage (HDCF%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of total High Danger Scoring Chances in games that team played that are for that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scoring Chance Goals For Percentage (SCGF%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of total goals off of scoring chances in games that team played that are for that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scoring Chance Shot Percentage (SCSH%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of Scoring Chance Shots for that team that were goals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Danger Goals For Percentage (HDGF%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of total goals off of High Danger Scoring Chances in games that team played that are for that team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Danger Shot Percentage (HDSH%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of High Danger Shots for that team that were goals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scoring Chance Save Percentage (SCSV%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of Scoring Chance Shots against that team that were not goals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Danger Save Percentage (HDSV%)&lt;/strong&gt; - Percentage of High Danger Shots against that team that were not goals&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/hockey-hangover/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/hockey-hangover/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The American Trap: Students can’t leave university because of financial security</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘This place is a hell hole for a broke, black woman like me’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/hc.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sophomore Ma’at Sargeant came back from class on the afternoon of May 1, 2017, ready to destress from her morning of classes with a nap. The semester was winding down and Sargeant was one of the many students preparing for finals. It was a normal day until she learned that bananas were strung through nooses and hung on trees across the American University campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This attack gained national media attention which led to an FBI investigation that is still ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2014, there has been a total of 21 hate-related attacks on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-20ISt&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/20ISt/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;304&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;20ISt&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;20ISt&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:556,&quot;200&quot;:388,&quot;300&quot;:371,&quot;400&quot;:346,&quot;500&quot;:346,&quot;700&quot;:304,&quot;800&quot;:304,&quot;900&quot;:304,&quot;1000&quot;:304},window.datawrapper[&quot;20ISt&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-20ISt&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;20ISt&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;20ISt&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;20ISt&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;20ISt&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;20ISt&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I knew that [the black community] was just a drop of the population at American, but never expected this to be an issue,” said Sargeant. 
Sargeant, a black woman, along with several of her peers considered leaving the university because of its unsafe and consistently hostile environment for students of color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite consistent cases of racially motivated incidents at the university, students said they cannot leave because they are financially tied to the university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice President of Campus Life and Inclusive Excellence, Dr. Fanta Aw worked in the office of Campus Life during the May 1 hate crime. In talking to students, Aw said they felt under attack and were traumatized by the events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The racial incident that happened at AU, that definitely had a significant impact on particularly African American students,” said Aw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sargeant explained the decline in her mental health over the years which she said was a direct result of the attacks at American University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It started with paranoia. I became paranoid about the people I was around. Then, it became anger and frustration,” Sargeant said. “I didn’t get to process the crimes because I had to act on it so quickly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the emotional and psychological effects these events had on AU students, Aw said they still stayed at the university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The retention rate of black students from [the class of 2020] were quite strong, the incident really left a poor taste in peoples mouths and negative perception of the institution, but it did not necessarily lead to students transferring out,” Aw said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said that students were compelled to stay because AU was offering them something other institutions would not be able to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Financial aid became a significant motivator for keeping people even when they weren’t happy,” Aw said. “I think people understood if they transferred they wouldn’t get that same level of aid.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-XpHCg&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/XpHCg/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;314&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;XpHCg&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;XpHCg&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:491,&quot;200&quot;:373,&quot;300&quot;:356,&quot;400&quot;:331,&quot;500&quot;:331,&quot;700&quot;:314,&quot;800&quot;:314,&quot;900&quot;:314,&quot;1000&quot;:314},window.datawrapper[&quot;XpHCg&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-XpHCg&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;XpHCg&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;XpHCg&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;XpHCg&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;XpHCg&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;XpHCg&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The retention rate data shows that the percentage of African American students stayed between 5 and 7 percent of the total population.
Sargeant took up the role of a student activist after conservative political commentator Milo Yiannopoulous came to the university. She and her peers demanded change from within the university to prevent hate speech on campus. She explained that she did not have any prior experience with activism before coming to American University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I didn’t come here to be an activist, it just played out that way. I was just a pissed off student who was tired of the environment I was forced to be in,” Sargeant said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even while pushing to make the campus a better place, Sargeant and other students considered leaving the university to go elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This place is a hell hole for a broke, black woman like me,” Sargeant said. “I would have transferred by now if I was not receiving money from American.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shirleyne McDonald, associate director of financial aid, observed students’ struggles to with stay at American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McDonald explained that many of her students came to her with questions about transferring as well as advice and support surrounding the hate crimes that occurred over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Students felt isolated and there was a push to get help and experience the community feeling again,” McDonald said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of attendance for a private university is based on several different aspects which are government funding, the financial need of the student, family contribution, tuition, mandatory fees, housing, meals, transportation, books and incidentals or personal costs, McDonald explained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-7tiUI&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/7tiUI/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;288&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;7tiUI&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;7tiUI&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:516,&quot;200&quot;:364,&quot;300&quot;:347,&quot;400&quot;:305,&quot;500&quot;:288,&quot;700&quot;:288,&quot;800&quot;:288,&quot;900&quot;:271,&quot;1000&quot;:271},window.datawrapper[&quot;7tiUI&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-7tiUI&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;7tiUI&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;7tiUI&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;7tiUI&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;7tiUI&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;7tiUI&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past five years, American University has worked to ensure that of the students who show financial need, all of them receive some form of a financial aid package, McDonald said. The university awarded $90 million in scholarships during that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total cost to attend American was just over $65,000 for the 2018-2019 academic year, the highest tuition and total cost of attendance have ever been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many students battle between choosing personal or financial safety and security on campus because of the amount of money they receive from the school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I feel like I had a lot of opportunity because of financial aid,” Lovesha Woods, a third-year political science student said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, Woods described her experience at American as one that has a great impact on her mental health. However, paying for her education outweighed her how she felts after the various attacks on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I transferred I wouldn’t have the money to pay for it. I’m low income and I live across the country, so that’s how that played out,” Woods said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Junior, Julian Baro, who identifies as Hispanic also considered transferring because of the treatment he saw towards African American students on campus, but financial reasons kept him at American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I was paying full pocket for this education and for this institution’s blatant racism, then yes, I would be at another school absolutely,” said Baro. “Most of it doesn’t come out of my pocket and thankfully I have other people paying for it because I can’t afford to.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students outweighed feelings of negativity because of substantial financial aid packages however, it’s doesn’t solve the fundamental issues American still grapples with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They know they don’t have to fix anything, they know we are pissed, they know we are miserable here, but they don’t care because they know we don’t have options,” said Sargeant. “They are more concerned with placating their students who have options to leave.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/hate-crimes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/hate-crimes/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>American University switches career databases</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The American University Career Center switched career database platforms in the spring of 2018 from AU CareerWeb to the widely used platform Handshake after 14 years using the previous service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its initial launch, Handshake has partnered with over 700 universities and 300,000 recruiters seeking eager employees. 14 million college students and young alumni are currently registered on the platform. The American University Career Center announced the switch from its previous service to Handshake via a school-wide email on May 7, 2018 and it went into effect one week later on May 14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handshake was founded by three Michigan Tech students in September 2013 as a platform for students to have easy access finding jobs. The service was officially launched in June 2014 and by July 2017, 5 million applications had gone through the platform. With an emphasis on inclusion, Handshake has built up a diverse staff and now serves as the primary job search platform for eight of the top ten HBCUs. Handshake operates in a similar style to Linkedin as well as other job-finding sites like Idealist.com and American University’s former platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American University Career Center partnered with Handshake with hopes of prioritizing students’ needs and making the job search experience simple. According to Nathan Slusher, the American University Career Center’s Director of Career Education and Outreach, “After 14 successful years of using the AU CareerWeb platform, the career services offices wanted to upgrade to a system that improved the student and employer user experience, expanded access to employers looking to recruit AU students and alumni, and included some additional features that help support students through every stage of the job search”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with having an updated and easy to navigate interface, Handshake delivers custom and personalized recommendations based on aspects like a student’s major, location, and previous searches. Students have the ability to create professional profiles and make them viewable to employers who are actively recruiting. Two additional unique features include a reviews tab where students can hear feedback from others who worked at a company, as well as a Q&amp;amp;A discussion board where they can ask general career-related or job-specific questions and receive advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Career Center, student engagement rates at American University are similar to those of peer institutions. American University currently has 8,200 approved employers and 17,355 active and expired job postings in its database. The switch to Handshake has widened the range of employers geographically with jobs available in the D.C. area and nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dayana Sarova, a junior in the School of International Service, used AU CareerWeb during her freshman and sophomore year to upload her résumé and cover letter for career fairs on campus. The internships she was hired for at the National Security Archive and Council on Foreign Relations were found through connections and by directly applying through each company’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Handshake was helpful in terms of seeing what options are out there… and kind of just going from there. But in terms of getting a job, I don’t know if it does a lot for you, and I don’t know what the advantage is of using Handshake over just applying straight from a company’s website,” said Sarova&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of 35 American University students and alumni surveyed, 11.1 percent have received jobs or internships through Handshake and 8.3 percent through AU CareerWeb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/poll1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haley Diamond, who graduated from AU in the spring of 2017, has used AU CareerWeb as a student looking for an internship as well as an employer when she was hiring a new intern to replace her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think I did only searches [in CareerWeb] because you type in your experience level, you would type in things you were interested in, and it would always limit what you can look at, so I never went through with an intern application,” said Diamond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finding an internship through the website Idealist at the recommendation of the Career Center, she eventually found a full-time position with them. When it came time to find her replacement as an intern, she posted on the jobs board at AU. “It was just a communications and development internship”, said Diamond, “so I would do the same listing on American as I would on Idealist or something similar, and you do an account, so they can verify that you’re a real thing, but [I] never heard anything. So, I can imagine that not many people use [sic] it. I mean, it was paid internship”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/poll2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bryony Whitelaw, a sophomore in the School of International Service, is just beginning her internship search in her college career, specifically looking into internships connected to the government. Having never used the platform AU CareerWeb and only making one appointment with the Career Center, she started-off using Handshake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Only one [internship] that I’m applying to was on Handshake. Everything else I found myself,” said Whitelaw. The rest of the internships she plans on applying for in the spring are government internships not found on Handshake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students find that AU CareerWeb and Handshake are good places to look for internships, but not a good route to apply from as they would hear little feedback from employers. Handshake’s public data does not share success rates in hiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/poll3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handshake has been praised by American University students for its clean interface and the customized recommendations it provides to students. Moving forward, students hope that Handshake can broaden the number of employers on the platform and increase diversity in job opportunities. Students feel that the service’s lack of jobs in areas like communications and the arts does not reflect the study body’s wide range of career aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond said of websites like AU Career Web and Handshake, “I feel like those things are intended to be useful, but 99 percent of the time, it’s meeting people at events, not online, that would really get you a job”.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/handshake/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/handshake/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sexual Assault in DC: Reporting numbers fall, but supporting hasn’t stopped</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Washington, D.C. has seen a recent decline in reported sexual assaults, which contrasts the national trend of increasing reporting. Although this decline may seem troubling at a time when movements such as #MeToo and #TimesUp have made headlines, D.C. is working hard to provide resources to sexual assault victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;national-data&quot;&gt;National Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FBI Uniform Crime Report releases national crime data each year. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2017/crime-in-the-u.s.-2017/tables/table-1&quot;&gt;FBI’s 2017 UCR&lt;/a&gt; shows reported sexual assaults are up by almost 20 percent from 2013. Between 2010 and 2017, reported assaults in the U.S. have varied year by year, but have been on the overall rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Oha3H/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;428&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:677.0208339999999,&quot;200&quot;:514.0208339999999,&quot;300&quot;:470.020834,&quot;400&quot;:470.020834,&quot;500&quot;:444.020834,&quot;700&quot;:428.020834,&quot;800&quot;:428.020834,&quot;900&quot;:428.020834,&quot;1000&quot;:428.020834},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;Oha3H&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more than 80 years, the FBI’s definition of &lt;em&gt;rape&lt;/em&gt; was: “Carnal knowledge of a female forcibly and against her will.” This definition, the legacy definition, limited the crimes that could be classified as rapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the FBI revised the definition of rape to be: “Penetration, no matter how slight, of the vagina or anus with any body part or object, or oral penetration by a sex organ of another person, without the consent of the victim.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new definition removed &lt;em&gt;forcibly&lt;/em&gt; and refers to consent, while also including victims of any gender. It also expanded the number of assaults that could be classified as rapes. When the FBI collects the total number of sexual assaults using the revised definition of rape, the totals are much higher than when using the legacy definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-RbiuT&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/RbiuT/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;540&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;RbiuT&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;RbiuT&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:701.020834,&quot;200&quot;:594.020834,&quot;300&quot;:567.020834,&quot;400&quot;:567.020834,&quot;500&quot;:567.020834,&quot;700&quot;:541.020834,&quot;800&quot;:541.020834,&quot;900&quot;:541.020834,&quot;1000&quot;:541.020834},window.datawrapper[&quot;RbiuT&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-RbiuT&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;RbiuT&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;RbiuT&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;RbiuT&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;RbiuT&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;RbiuT&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dc-data&quot;&gt;D.C. Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While national reporting statistics are climbing, D.C.’s reporting numbers are falling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In D.C., sexual assaults are referred to in data collection as &lt;em&gt;sex abuse&lt;/em&gt;. D.C.’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://advance.lexis.com/documentpage/?pdmfid=1000516&amp;amp;crid=19301465-60a1-4fed-a329-b7e96a389489&amp;amp;nodeid=AAEAABAABABPAABAAB&amp;amp;nodepath=%2fROOT%2fAAE%2fAAEAAB%2fAAEAABAAB%2fAAEAABAABABP%2fAAEAABAABABPAAB%2fAAEAABAABABPAABAAB&amp;amp;level=6&amp;amp;haschildren=&amp;amp;populated=false&amp;amp;title=%C2%A7+22-3001.+Definitions.&amp;amp;config=00JABiNDg1YzdlZi1kMDFiLTQ5YmQtYjM2Yi03ZWY3MmNiNmE1NTEKAFBvZENhdGFsb2f7r915sHTEilgUZv8sJAwq&amp;amp;pddocfullpath=%2fshared%2fdocument%2fstatutes-legislation%2furn%3acontentItem%3a5CC4-MNP1-6NSS-B4WG-00008-00&amp;amp;ecomp=-kL8kkk&amp;amp;prid=c2de2573-cef7-40f8-97ac-fbd33ba55620&quot;&gt;definition&lt;/a&gt; of sex abuse is almost identical to the FBI’s revised definition of rape, but the trends in reporting rates are different. In D.C., the number of reported sexual assaults increased steadily from 2010 until 2016, but then drops off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-zmn0W&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/zmn0W/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;zmn0W&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;zmn0W&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:480.020834,&quot;200&quot;:426.020834,&quot;300&quot;:426.020834,&quot;400&quot;:400.020834,&quot;500&quot;:400.020834,&quot;700&quot;:400.020834,&quot;800&quot;:400.020834,&quot;900&quot;:400.020834,&quot;1000&quot;:400.020834},window.datawrapper[&quot;zmn0W&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-zmn0W&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;zmn0W&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;zmn0W&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;zmn0W&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;zmn0W&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;zmn0W&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Metropolitan Police Department uses the FBI’s Uniform Crime Reporting system, which closes cases based on arrests and exceptional means, known as an exceptional clearance. Exceptional clearance is defined as a case that is cleared when police have enough evidence to make an arrest but cannot due to reasons outside their control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MPD data, the Sexual Assault Unit cleared more than 50 percent of their cases between 2014 and 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-S09nG&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/S09nG/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;582&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;S09nG&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;S09nG&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:763,&quot;200&quot;:660,&quot;300&quot;:621,&quot;400&quot;:582,&quot;500&quot;:582,&quot;700&quot;:557,&quot;800&quot;:557,&quot;900&quot;:557,&quot;1000&quot;:557},window.datawrapper[&quot;S09nG&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-S09nG&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;S09nG&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;S09nG&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;S09nG&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;S09nG&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;S09nG&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent ProPublica investigation revealed that police departments across the country are closing cases without an arrest using the rule of exceptional clearance, which is meant to be used only in extreme circumstances. However, MPD does not follow this trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elisabeth Olds, the SAVRAA Independent Expert Consultant contracted by the Executive Office of the Mayor, is responsible for monitoring the way the D.C. handles sexual assault cases. Olds confirmed that the MPD is following appropriate case closing protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By and large, as a unit, the Sexual Assault Unit is not inappropriately closing cases,” Olds said. “These people work absurdly hard.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MPD has been responsive to victims of sexual assault in recent years. A 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;https://ovsjg.dc.gov/sites/default/files/dc/sites/ovsjg/page_content/attachments/SAVRAA%20Independent%20Consultant%20Reports_0.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; released by the Office of Victim Services and Justice Grants said that 77 percent of victims interviewed reported that they felt believed and detectives were empathetic to their situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MPD did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;victim-services&quot;&gt;Victim Services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D.C. has a network of politicians, advocates and medical professionals that are working hard to ensure that victims have the support they need to pursue their cases, if they choose to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key resource for victims seeking justice is a piece of legislation called the Sexual Assault Victims’ Rights Act of 2014. SAVRA grants victims the right to have an advocate present during forensic exams and law enforcement questioning, have their sexual assault evidence kits processed within 90 days, and to be informed of the results of any toxicology or DNA testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regina Curran, American University’s Title IX coordinator, said that providing victims with a bill of rights is a helpful first step in the case review process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There could be no better change than empowering victims and giving them a voice that is taken seriously,” Curran said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Mayor Muriel Bowser proposed an updated version of SAVRA to the D.C. Council. Bowser’s proposal, known as SAVRA 2.0, included provisions that would expand the law’s coverage to include victims between the ages of 12 and 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SAVRA 2.0, which is still in committee in the D.C. Council, would expand the pool of advocates available to sexual assault victims to ensure that everyone has access to an advocate. However, non-profit organizations and service providers for victims find SAVRA 2.0 controversial. Leise Gergley, a senior case manager for the Network of Victim Recovery DC, said that allowing anyone to assist a victim at the crime scene could hurt their case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Saying that anyone could be a sexual assault advocate could also be problematic if they don’t have the right training,” Gergley said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gergely has assisted victims in many different ways, from recruiting advocates to go to hospitals to going to court with those seeking protection orders. NVRDC has seen an increase in the number of victims coming into the hospital to get forensic exams in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think the organizations that aren’t law enforcement are seeing more of an uptick because people are looking for that care,” Gergley said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gergley attributes the media as a major factor in the discretion between the number of cases reported and the number of victims seeking assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the media, the way that they’ve seen people who come forward be treated in the criminal process or the various other processes we’ve seen survivors stand up for…I think it’s really discouraging for folks,” Gergley said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NVRDC is an advocate arm of DC’s Sexual Assault Response Team, which is made up of nurses, police, medical examiners and other nonprofits to provide care and legal help for victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colleen Gallopin, Executive Director of D.C. Forensic Nurse Examiners and one of SART’s co-chairs, said that the bringing this group of people together is “groundbreaking” for finding the best practices in sexual assault response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SART gives the key players in sexual assault prevention a chance to brainstorm as a team. When a forensic lab technician suggests a more accurate data collection method for the forensic nurses to implement, the Metropolitan Police Officers and prosecutors have a chance to weigh in. If a call for change by one branch of SART is echoed by another, that new protocol will be implemented, so long as it does not impede the prosecution process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re able to move the District a little closer to whatever that ideal is,” Gallopin said.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/dc-sexual-assaults/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/dc-sexual-assaults/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cremation mercury emissions a cause for concern</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2002, Ray-Brent Marsh’s life was ruined. Charged with multiple counts of theft by deception and abuse of a corpse, Marsh hid a third of the hundreds of bodies brought to his crematorium over the years. When asked in court why he had done it, Marsh said, “[if you’re] looking for an answer, I cannot give you one.” In 2007, Marsh’s lawyer McCracken Poston had an answer: mercury poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the explanation of a criminal defense lawyer may seem dubious at first, mercury poisoning is well-known to cause bizarre behavior and even insanity. Hatmakers of the 19th century, who used mercury in the manufacturing process, were so often afflicted with mercury poisoning, that it conceived the name “Mad Hatter’s Disease.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe that Ray-Brent Marsh, while living and working at the crematory, became a modern-day ‘Mad Hatter,’” wrote Poston in a press release. “An external, environmental cause claimed…the literal sanity and judgment of Ray-Brent Marsh.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marsh’s case is just one example of what could be a much larger issue. Due in part to the softening of religious expectations surrounding death, and the high costs associated with conventional burial, cremation has become increasingly popular. According to the National Funeral Directors Association (NFDA), 2015 was the first year on record where cremation eclipsed burial as the most widespread method of body disposal. However, as the prevalence of cremation grows, the environmental and public health impact of the practice grows, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/rates.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;According to the 2018 NFDA Cremation and Burial Report, cremation will account for nearly 80 percent of all body disposals by 2035 (2020-35 are projections).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The costs that go into a traditional burial can be daunting. Cremation can save an ordinary consumer nearly $10,000, which has contributed to its recent increase in popularity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/costs.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The median costs for a traditional burial funeral, totalling over $16,000 according to 2018 NFDA Cremation &amp;amp; Burial Report. Cremation, in comparison, typically costs less than $6,500.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This increase, when combined with the absence of regulations within the cremation industry and the prevalence of mercury in dental fillings and medical devices such as pacemakers (both extremely common in the elderly who are soon to be cremated), suggests a massive increase in mercury emissions could lie ahead. But mercury is not the only concern. Carbon dioxide and other toxins emitted from cremation, alongside the nonexistent regulations, also contributes to the environmental damage according to researcher Alexis Cain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data from the Cremation Association of North America (CANA) shows that there were just over a million cremations in 2011. A conservative average of mercury released per cremation is 2.9 grams - although some scientists have observed as much as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ejnet.org/crematoria/reindl.pdf&quot;&gt;8.6 grams released&lt;/a&gt;. This means over three metric tons of mercury are being released by cremations annually - more than 10 times the current EPA estimate. This calculation is supported by a 2007 paper by former EPA scientist Alexis Cain, who arrived at a very similar number. Cain said that the EPA’s estimate is based on tests which measured the output of mercury from stacks, but that the tests had a very small sample size and may not have even been accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/Map.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Per capita  mercury emissions from cremation as of 2011. Rhode Island, Maine and Montana lead the nation, each with over 1.6 kilograms per 100,000 residents.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The issue is cremating one body at a time,” Cain said. “Measuring one stack burning one body isn’t going to give an accurate estimate. The mercury has to go somewhere.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cain said that almost all of the mercury in the body would end up being released into the air and not stay in the ashes of the deceased. 
“Mercury is very volatile at room temperature,” he said. “It evaporates easily. [The idea that it might not all be released] seems very unlikely to me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When those fumes are released, they can harm both the environment and the cremator. When the hair of Ray-Brent Marsh was tested for mercury contamination, his results gave telltale signs of a massive previous mercury exposure. Marsh’s father, the previous owner of the crematory, died suffering from a number of unexplained medical conditions. His father’s “Parkinson’s-like” symptoms, neuropathy, and declining mental health were classic signs of mercury poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mercury, however, is not the only environmental problem with cremation. According to the Calgary Co-Operative Memorial Society, organic compounds are also emitted from cremation, which react with other toxins under combustion conditions to form polychlorinated dibenzodioxins and polychlorinated dibenzofurans, both of which are carcinogens. A study by CANA found standard filtering techniques for crematorium fumes had little effect on the toxins released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cremations also contribute to global warming. Every cremation produces 180 kilograms of carbon dioxide - equal to burning 20 gallons of gasoline, according to CANA’s Executive Director Barbara Kemmis. “It’s the equivalent of heating a home for a week,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/CO2.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Estimated carbon dioxide emissions from cremation (based on CANA figures).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making matters worse, regulations of the cremation industry are lax at best. There are no federal laws regulating mercury or carbon dioxide emissions from crematories, and most states have not acted either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Cremators don’t have any controls designed to remove mercury,” said Cain. Other countries have recognized the harmful effects of cremating corpses with dental amalgam. Scotland, for instance, requires dental fillings and medical devices to be removed prior to cremation. There is no such standard in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional burial is not necessarily a better alternative.  According to the Berkeley Planning Journal, traditional burials in the United States use 30 million pounds of hardwood, 2,700 tons of copper and bronze, 104,272 tons of steel, and 1,636,000 tons of concrete for vaults and caskets annually. The wood alone needed for caskets, is “equivalent to 4 million square acres of forest, which contains enough trees to…supply the wood needed to build over 90,000 homes”, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://safepassageurns.com/&quot;&gt;safepassageurns.com&lt;/a&gt;. That’s an area almost twice the size of Yellowstone National Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse still, the embalming process releases toxic chemicals such as formaldehyde, glutaraldehyde, phenol and many others. According to the NFDA, burials leak 827,000 gallons of formaldehyde-based embalming fluids into American soil and waterways each year. The same chemicals are used to finish the wood on caskets. Burial can even have a higher carbon dioxide emissions rate than cremation, but the issue is a matter of debate, and “depends on which formula you use,” according to Kemmis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are environmentally friendly alternatives that are gaining popularity. On such alternative is “green burial,” which involve simply wrapping the body in cloth and burying it without a casket or embalming fluid. Another option is “biocremation,” which uses a low-energy chemical process to cremate the body without releasing mercury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The environmental damage done by cremation is a quiet topic. Beside single hearing before the House Subcommittee on Domestic Policy in 2008, federal and state governments have kept relatively silent on the issue. The long-term damage remains to be seen, but Cain says it’s still cause for concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The mercury issue will solve itself in the very long term as people get fewer amalgam fillings,” Cain said. “But for now, it’s a real issue.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/cremation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/cremation/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>For AU basketball, the Princeton offense may be their root of inefficiency</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mike Brennan’s unfolded arms dropped down to his waist and carried with them the weight of frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With just seconds remaining, American blew a shot to take the lead with a wide-open three from the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We had a couple shots down the stretch where you have to make them to win a game like this,” Brennan said &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theeagleonline.com/article/2018/12/au-mens-basketball-falls-to-wagner-after-late-surge&quot;&gt;after the contest&lt;/a&gt;, “and we didn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American University’s 64-58 defeat to Wagner is just one of the program’s 83 losses in the five seasons since it last made the NCAA tournament in 2014. Head coach Brennan was in just his first year at the helm of the program, yet coached his team to an appearance in the second round of the tournament and a Patriot League championship. Brennan, a former Princeton University basketball player, installed his alma mater’s offense into AU’s everyday gameplan. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/sports/colleges/with-a-little-help-from-pete-carril-mike-brennan-has-american-basketball-off-to-a-hot-start-in-his-first-season/2014/01/25/85cbe1fc-85fb-11e3-8742-668814928ae4_story.html?utm_term=.a36942f7fc26&quot;&gt;Fans and media&lt;/a&gt; considered his offense one of American’s most important additions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with little success in the years since, one has to wonder what’s gone wrong on the court. Is AU’s Princeton style attack actually effective, or has it held the team back? Analytics, as acquired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sports-reference.com/cbb/seasons/2018-advanced-school-stats.html&quot;&gt;Sports Reference&lt;/a&gt;, suggest American has been ill-equipped to run the offense for years – exposing a major inefficiency in their gameplan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-SxCqc&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/SxCqc/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;383&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;SxCqc&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;SxCqc&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:620,&quot;200&quot;:488,&quot;300&quot;:427,&quot;400&quot;:427,&quot;500&quot;:400,&quot;700&quot;:383,&quot;800&quot;:383,&quot;900&quot;:383,&quot;1000&quot;:383},window.datawrapper[&quot;SxCqc&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-SxCqc&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;SxCqc&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;SxCqc&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;SxCqc&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;SxCqc&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;SxCqc&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in the 2017-18 season the Eagles were ranked just 325th out of 351 programs in terms of offensive rating. This statistic rates how efficient a team is at producing points for its offense, meaning that AU ranks among the lowest schools in the country at scoring efficient buckets. That year, the team won just six of its 34 games, finishing the season with the 338th best win-loss percentage in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, ranking among the bottom-tier in terms of offensive rating is bad for AU basketball. But it is especially worse for a program whose offense is fundamentally designed to slow down the game and find the most efficient shot possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pioneered by coach Pete Carrill at Princeton, and discipled by Mike Brennan, the strategy relies on constantly moving the ball between teammates. According to Dr. Jim Gels, a coach of more than 30 years who also provides resources and information to young coaches, the Princeton is highly complicated. It requires all five players on the court to be skilled at dribbling, passing and outside shooting. When asked about the offense’s basic requirements, Gels referred to his teachings on his consultation site, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coachesclipboard.net/&quot;&gt;Coach’s Clipboard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘“They must possess some ‘basketball sense’ or IQ in order to read the actions of teammates and of the defense,” Dr. Gels wrote. “The offense breaks down into a series of 3-man plays, with some 1-on-1 play also possible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott Greenman, an assistant coach at American, is no stranger to the offense. Having coached at Princeton himself, Greenman has spent the last 12 years practicing many of the same principles as he learned at Princeton, though not necessarily the same actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Some ‘Princeton Offenses’ probably run more ‘set plays’ than we do and may focus more on the actions than the teaching points or concepts,” he said. “We believe in running an offense that involves everyone, makes everyone better, and gives our team the best chance to win. We focus a lot on playing unselfishly and working together to get the best shot possible each time down the court.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an email, Dr. Gels said that when it is run efficiently the Princeton holds many benefits. Players are always trying to help each other get open, he said. Since the offense relies on outside shooting, having a capable center who can step away from the paint and shoot effectively is a major bonus of the system. In doing that, the offense stretches the floor and imposes a real challenge on opposing defenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-pSaj7&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/pSaj7/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;421&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;pSaj7&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;pSaj7&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:722,&quot;200&quot;:519,&quot;300&quot;:448,&quot;400&quot;:448,&quot;500&quot;:421,&quot;700&quot;:404,&quot;800&quot;:377,&quot;900&quot;:377,&quot;1000&quot;:377},window.datawrapper[&quot;pSaj7&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-pSaj7&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;pSaj7&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;pSaj7&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;pSaj7&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;pSaj7&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;pSaj7&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2013-14 season, Brennan’s AU Eagles demonstrated how successful the Princeton can be, given the right players. Comparatively, American made a greater percentage of three-point shots on average than the average of each school in the NCAA. In the Patriot League alone, AU ranked first of all teams in average three-point field goal percentage, converting 40.1 percent of their shots. In terms of total average field goal percentage, AU ranked as high as eighth in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why hasn’t that success carried over to today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all its benefits, the Princeton also has its challenges. According to Greenman, the offense isn’t the easiest to teach players because it requires players who have developed advanced skill sets. Teaching players how to make good decisions on the court, he said, takes a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s not nearly as complicated as it’s made out to be – it just requires a good feel for the game,” Greenman said. “Like any offense, it takes a little while to learn and feel comfortable in, but I don’t think there’s much more of a learning curve for the Princeton offense than most offenses in college. Every offense takes a little while to learn or master, and the more you know how to play, the easier it is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Gels, however, disagrees. According to him, the offense is often too complicated for younger players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“First, you usually won’t have five really skilled, interchangeable players at that age, and they won’t have the basketball IQ yet,” he said. “Younger players aren’t ready to be shooting up 3-pointers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially problematic for teams that shoot poorly from the perimeter. In the 2017-18 season, AU ranked 242nd in three-point field goal percentage. The Princeton is a bad system for teams that struggle from three-point range, according to Dr. Gels. Instead, they should shift to an offense that “revolves around the post players” rather than their guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offensive stagnation, bad shots and turnovers are the three biggest indicators the offense is at a stand-still, he said. The most helpful metric for evaluating performance, however, is player efficiency rating (PER). This metric attempts to summarize any given player’s contributions on the court in one number. In other words, it is a rating of their overall statistical performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-KyZPz&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/KyZPz/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;318&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;KyZPz&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;KyZPz&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:426,&quot;200&quot;:372,&quot;300&quot;:345,&quot;400&quot;:345,&quot;500&quot;:318,&quot;700&quot;:318,&quot;800&quot;:318,&quot;900&quot;:318,&quot;1000&quot;:318},window.datawrapper[&quot;KyZPz&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-KyZPz&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;KyZPz&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;KyZPz&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;KyZPz&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;KyZPz&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;KyZPz&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per AU men’s basketball’s advanced metrics, as collected by Sports Reference, the program’s average PER has steadily declined in most years since the success of the 2013-14 season. This means that on average AU basketball players have played less efficiently over time, though this is not true for &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; players. Star point-guard Sa’eed Nelson, for example, has increased his PER in each of his three seasons at AU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the average player has become increasingly inefficient over time, both Dr. Gels and Coach Greenman suggest that young players can grow into the Princeton system. “Essentially, just like any offense, having an older team with experience makes a world of difference,” Greenman said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they develop, they may adapt and become more efficient players, as Sa’eed Nelson has done over time. But as a program overall, AU’s inefficiency has only become more apparent. Their offense is stagnant, they shoot poorly from outside and they play inefficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But should AU really overhaul the way they coach their offense? Maybe not, but it is one of several remaining options for the program. Yes, AU can replace the Princeton and start recruiting and coaching players who fit a system more tailored to their talents. They could double-down on the Princeton and gamble on their young players growing into the gameplan. Or, using the data to their benefit, the team can focus on eliminating the areas of their game that are the least efficient. They can improve as shooters, passers and dribblers. Coaching staff can draw up new ways to expose defenses with a good look at a good shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Greenman, AU already reviews a “good amount” of analytical data, though he was reluctant to give away any secrets. On top of analytics, the coaching staff pays close attention to practices, where they watch for effort and attention to detail. Numbers, after all, only really paint half the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data isn’t all bad for American, but until they do something about, it may only get worse.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 13:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/basketball/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2018/fall-2018/basketball/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
