<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COMM-260 Quant Methods &amp; Data Viz (Fall 2020)</title>
    <description>Final projects from students in Quantitative Methods &amp; Data Visualization at American University Fall 2020.  
</description>
    <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 16:00:48 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 16:00:48 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yelp ratings don’t reflect inspection grades, and restaurant owners aren’t happy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2016, writer Hana Nobel attempted to dine at five of San Francisco’s worst Yelp-rated restaurants. The experiment was cut short after Nobel got food poisoning at the fourth restaurant on the list. The buzz generated by Nobel’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebolditalic.com/i-visited-san-francisco-s-worst-rated-yelp-restaurants-and-got-food-poisoning-the-bold-italic-e326c6b1d47b&quot;&gt;subsequent article&lt;/a&gt;, published by the Bold Italic, fed into an easy consumer conclusion: that low Yelp ratings correlate with unsanitary restaurant conditions. Jeremy Stoppelman, CEO of Yelp, reinforced this conclusion, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jeremys/status/634173246271676416&quot;&gt;retweeting Nobel’s article, writing: “What happens when you eat at a number of restaurants with extremely low @yelp ratings? Bet you can guess…”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;What happens when you eat at a number of restaurants with extremely low &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Yelp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@yelp&lt;/a&gt; ratings? Bet you can guess... &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/kfYFzhJicn&quot;&gt;http://t.co/kfYFzhJicn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jeremy Stoppelman (@jeremys) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jeremys/status/634173246271676416?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 20, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presumed correlation between low Yelp ratings and inspection grades has floated around in public thought for years, much to the dismay of restaurant owners. However, an analysis between public Yelp data and restaurant inspection grades in Maricopa County, Ariz., shows that there is no definitive correlation between low Yelp ratings and inspection grades. Average Yelp ratings are around 3.5 stars, regardless of inspection score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4582513&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Average inspection scores are in the 90s (A grades) across Yelp star ratings. Restaurants with 1-star or 5-star Yelp ratings, the highest and lowest possible ratings, are outliers. Only 3 percent of Maricopa restaurants in the analysis have a 5-star Yelp rating, and only 2 percent have a 5-star rating. Eighty-six percent of restaurants are concentrated within the 2.5-star to 4.5-star range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4606209&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing on Yelp’s platform offers a clear indication of cleanliness: not food cuisine tags, not zip codes, not even high Yelp ratings. Yelp users cannot use the forum to predict whether or not a restaurant is sanitary, yet, as Stoppelman’s Tweet demonstrates, the forum promotes the idea that they can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4584568&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Maricopa County Restaurant Averages by Zip Code&quot; aria-label=&quot;chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-hUSTw&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/hUSTw/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;938&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobel herself does not believe that Yelp ratings are generally indicative of bad sanitation. She concludes that most reviews usually focus on food quality and customer service, instead of sanitation practices. Though unfortunate, the results of Nobel’s experiment were not necessarily unexpected–she had compiled her list by searching Yelp for the keywords “worst” and “food poisoning.” She still doesn’t take Yelp reviews at face value, especially for indicating a restaurant’s sanitation level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Things have to be really bad for someone to notice and put that in a review–like cockroaches on the floor or pigeons in the restaurant,” She says. The latter Nobel experienced in Chinatown Restaurant during her experiment. She notes, “People don’t usually know what goes on in the kitchen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-impact-of-yelp-ratings-on-restaurants&quot;&gt;The impact of Yelp ratings on restaurants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restaurant owners are well-aware of the distance between Yelp ratings and inspection scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rachel and Tim Lyons co-owned two high-end restaurants in Durham, NC: Primal Foods &amp;amp; Spirits and Blu Seafood and Bar. Both restaurants closed in 2018, but Rachel Lyons remembers the negative impact Yelp had on both businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before joining the restaurant business, the Lyonses heard that Yelp would prioritize a restaurant’s negative reviews unless the restaurant chose to advertise with them. Many businesses complained about this issue in the early 2010s and the topic garnered massive media attention. The website &lt;a href=&quot;https://yelp-sucks.com/tell-your-yelp-story/&quot;&gt;www.yelp-sucks.com&lt;/a&gt; was created for small business owners to voice their frustrations with the forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Yelp reached out to the Lyonses with an advertisement opportunity for their restaurants, they declined. As a result, they noticed negative reviews populating the top of their Yelp page. The bigger problem, Rachel Lyons notes, is that many of the reviews were unfair, posted by customers who either didn’t give the restaurant a chance to redeem itself for a mistake, or did not understand upscale dining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mistakes do happen,” Lyons says. “Unfortunately, people can go to Yelp and just write down a bad review without even giving that opportunity to make everything better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blu was a small, locally-owned restaurant that sourced its seafood from high-quality sellers. Lyons says that a frequent problem was that customers would judge the restaurant by Red Lobster standards, and complain on Yelp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“[High-quality] ingredients cost more,” she says. “When someone would then write a review about the portion sizes being too small, that, just with their stars, brings our rating down.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Yelp does not have a system of verification that proves customers ate at a restaurant or used a business. Lyons remembers one example of a rival business owner leaving a fraudulent review on Primal’s Yelp page using a fake account. The Lyonses contacted Yelp in the hopes of having the review removed. They were unsuccessful. Though Primal is now closed, the fraudulent review is still on its Yelp page. Eleven Yelpers marked it as “useful.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s really your word against the public,” Lyons says. “Someone who may not have even ever come to your restaurant but simply doesn’t like you for another reason can go online and make anything up and be published. And that hurts your business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preference-based-reviews&quot;&gt;Preference-based reviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of fraudulent and misplaced reviews, many Yelp reviews are preference-based. In Maricopa County, where around 24,000 businesses are listed on Yelp, the phrase “my preference” appears in 240 unique reviews, as does the phrase “for my taste.” Yelp only allows 240 results per keyword search, so the real figures are likely much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Yelper Aileen C. ate at Roaring Fork Restaurant in Maricopa County, she left a 3.5-star review. She wrote: “Disclaimer: I only went to the happy hour… Citrus Mojito: Eh. Not great. It wasn’t citrus-y enough for me, but that may be just personal preference… Overall, it was fine but I do want to try it for regular dinner one night because I have had friends give Roaring Fork raving reviews.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lyons thinks that the Yelp Elite program might have something to do with preference-based reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yelp Elite is a program in which, after posting a high number of reviews and regularly engaging with other users on Yelp, a Yelper earns a special profile tag that labels them as “Elite.” Elite members are invited to exclusive events hosted by Yelp. Through Yelp Elite, Yelpers are rewarded for writing reviews when they may not have otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;yelps-health-scores&quot;&gt;Yelp’s health scores&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after Nobel’s article was published, Yelp started posting “health scores” on most restaurant pages, a practice that had previously only been instituted in a handful of cities. The health scores do not represent recent state or county grades, but rather an algorithmic average based on past scores and violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem with this system, Lyons notes, is that inspection violations don’t always represent cleanliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“People always think it’s just about how clean your restaurant is,” she says, “but really it has a lot to do with where things are located. Sometimes, because these inspections are not known in advance, the inspector will just show up and you may be in the midst of receiving a shipment. You can be unfairly graded simply because you’re just in the midst of putting things away.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restaurateurs often refer to inspection scores as a “snapshot” of time that does not represent their overall reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her Mercury News article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mercurynews.com/2018/08/09/yelps-new-health-scores-dont-mean-what-you-think-they-do/&quot;&gt;“What’s in a Number: Yelp’s New Health Scores Don’t Mean What You Think They Do,”&lt;/a&gt; writer Jessica Yadegaran unpacks the controversies surrounding Yelp’s health scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the article, Yadegaran talks to Golden Gate Restaurant Association representative Gwyneth Borden. Borden reinforces the unreliable nature of inspection scores, saying, “The things you got in trouble for, you fix. You have a reinspection within one week. You have to live with the bad score.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yelp’s system, Borden concludes, is neither transparent nor fair. She notes that, in 2015, San Francisco businesses that were flagged for major violations lost business by an average of 15 percent. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.yelp.com/2018/03/study-low-hygiene-scores-yelp-lead-decrease-consumer-purchase-intent&quot;&gt;2018 study&lt;/a&gt; promoted by Yelp found that Yelp’s health scores decrease traffic for businesses with low scores by 12 percent compared to businesses with high scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lyons, Borden, and Nobel conclude that Yelp yields an unfair and unreliable power over businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem-with-inspection-data&quot;&gt;The problem with inspection data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For consumers who care about restaurant sanitation, state and county records may be as unreliable as Yelp’s health scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Maricopa County, for example, receiving a public inspection grade is voluntary for restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sanitarian Jaime Vinaras works for the Maricopa Health Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He describes that, while the Maricopa Health Department is responsible for the county’s mandatory inspections, restaurants choose whether or not they want their grades to be public. If not, their scores are published on the Maricopa Health Department website as “Not Participating.” Specific violations are not made public, but the count of violations and past A grades in the past three years are. The Maricopa Health Department has repeatedly asserted that this information is enough for members of the public to understand a restaurant’s overall safety level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nothing in state law in Arizona says that a restaurant has to have a grade,” says Vinaras. As a result, of the 24,000 Maricopa County restaurant inspections between Aug. 4, 2016, and July, 25, 2019, 44 percent were marked as “Not Participating.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4583935&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Maricopa Health Department law, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maricopa.gov/DocumentCenter/View/5861/Grade-Card-Guidance-Document-PDF?bidId=&quot;&gt;restaurants are given the choice to have their inspection grades published prior to inspection&lt;/a&gt;. Even though inspections occur randomly, when they do, restaurant owners can make educated guesses about their business’ sanitation. Perhaps unsurprisingly, of the 13,544 restaurant inspections with published grades, 82 percent were A grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incentive for a restaurant to choose public grading is to showcase cleanliness to customers, but some restaurants still receive imperfect grades. Out of the 24,000 inspections, 83 received D grades, 302 received C grades, and 2,073 received B grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vinaras says that the Maricopa Health Department hasn’t seen any glaring trends of restaurants with low-inspection scores being concentrated in certain cuisine types or locations. He chose not to comment on the accuracy of Yelp’s health scores, but emphasized that the company’s system was different from that of the Maricopa Health Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Maricopa County Average Household Income by Zip Code&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-dVr6d&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/dVr6d/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;626&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Average Yelp Stars by Zip Code&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Q4ROg&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Q4ROg/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;626&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Maricopa County Average Inspection Grades by Zip Code&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-T5S3a&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/T5S3a/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;640&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only clear external indicator of a restaurant’s cleanliness, he notes, is whether or not it has Active Managerial Control (AMC), a designated food safety management team. “Restaurants that have active food safety management have better control over food safety practices,” he says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no existing database of restaurants with safety management teams, and this information is not as accessible to the average consumer as, for example, a Yelp rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, inspection grading systems like Maricopa’s are the reason for Yelp’s algorithmic health scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s an incentive for health inspectors and restaurateurs to have esoteric language that keeps consumers out of the loop,” Luther Lowe, Yelp’s vice president for public policy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://washingtoncitypaper.com/article/184847/do-yelps-health-scores-accurately-capture-the-cleanliness-of-dc-restaurants/&quot;&gt;told the Washington City Paper&lt;/a&gt;. “We’re trying to give them a seat at the table.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;## A world without Yelp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, restaurateur Billy Godwin took over the Sunrise Cafe in Maricopa County after the original owners lost the business during the Covid-19 lockdown. Though the cafe has an added “New” in its name, the original Yelp page still exists, with corresponding contact information, hours of operation, and recent reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restaurant has a 3-star rating, a relatively low score for the Maricopa area. When asked about Yelp’s impact on his business, Goodwin was surprised to learn the restaurant was even listed. He says online reviews aren’t something he plans to incorporate into the New Sunrise Cafe’s business model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re a family-run business,” Godwin says. “You want to make everyone happy, but we focus on customers who walk through the door and the food we serve them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only a few months into its new ownership, business at the New Sunrise Cafe is booming.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/resaurant-inspections-yelp/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/resaurant-inspections-yelp/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why DC Metrorail has been hit the hardest by the pandemic, and what its future is riding on</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 30th, 2020, Mayor Bowser issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://coronavirus.dc.gov/release/mayor-bowser-issues-stay-home-order&quot;&gt;stay-at-home-order&lt;/a&gt; for Washington, D.C. The order was an attempt to curb the rising numbers of COVID-19 cases across the region and the nation. A condition of the order was that residents only engage in essential travel, which included essential work and activities, such as visiting a doctor. All forms of transportation quickly declined as those who could took to a new life indoors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this same time, Apple began tracking daily requests for directions in Apple Maps. The data served as an entry point to understanding COVID-19 mobility trends. In D.C., the mobility data illustrated the effects of COVID-19 and Bowser’s stay-at-home-order. Over time, routing requests for walking, driving, and public transit across the region collectively dropped. Some dropped more than others. Public transit requests fell significantly faster than those for walking or driving, hitting their lowest point mid-April. As COVID-19 cases in D.C. slowly receded and travel crept back up, routing requests for walking and driving increased significantly faster than requests for public transit. Nearing the end of November, public transit requests have begun to fall once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washington D.C. Mobility Trends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Washington D.C. Mobility Trends&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-IiGop&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/IiGop/4/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we account for the disparity in routing requests for public transit? The Transportation Research Board’s Executive Director Neil Pedersen said D.C. is unique in its high population of “choice riders.” While “transit captives” have no alternative to public transit, choice riders have more flexibility in their travel options, said Pedersen. Washington has a higher percentage of choice riders. “They are the ones where if people are afraid to be using a system because of COVID-19 or there are significant reductions in service, they are most likely to not come back.” D.C.’s high population of choice riders has more flexibility in their travel options and can easily turn to alternatives when public transit is no longer the safest option. This explains why routing requests for public transit dropped more than those for walking or driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public transit in D.C. comes in two major forms: Metrobus and Metrorail. Ridership rates for both systems decreased, consistent with the Apple mobility data. More interestingly, Metrorail lost significantly more riders than Metrobus, according to an analysis of Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority (WMATA) data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D.C. Bus and Rail Ridership 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;DC Bus and Rail Ridership 2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-8h7Tx&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/8h7Tx/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This difference relates back to the idea of “captive” and “choice” riders. Washington is dominated by professional office workers, and these folks fall into the category of choice riders. As Pedersen explained, “Rail ridership in particular is dominated by central business district office workers. Bus has much more been serving essential workers, those who have to go to work for health care or other essential services where they clearly have to be on the job as opposed to being able to work from home.” Since the Metrorail is more popular among choice riders who can turn to alternative forms of transportation or perhaps work from home, Metrorail has lost the most riders. This holds true when comparing Metrobus and Metrorail ridership data from 2020 to that of 2019, too. Metrobus ridership decreased by an average of 62%, while Metrorail ridership decreased by an average of 84%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D.C. Metrobus ridership 2019-2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&quot;DC Metrobus Ridership 2019-2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-tVb2q&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/tVb2q/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DC Metrorail ridership 2019-2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&quot;DC Metrorail Ridership 2019-2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-ldASz&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/ldASz/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WMATA is facing severe monetary loss as a result. Metrorail alone has lost nearly $500 million in 2020. Metro board released a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wmata.com/about/board/meetings/board-pdfs/upload/3A-GM-FY2022-Proposed-Budget.pdf&quot;&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; on November 30th outlining the cutbacks they will have to make in 2021 if they don’t receive funding. The proposal would eliminate weekend Metrorail service entirely, close 19 stations, decrease rail service to every 30 minutes, and cut bus service by 45% of pre-pandemic levels. Eno Center for Transportation Policy Analyst Romic Aevaz said the proposed cutbacks would affect essential workers the most. “If transit agencies are still in a bad situation and they have to cut back service, it’s going to hurt the essential workers the most. Essential workers are the backbone of the economy, and their movement is critical.” Captive riders, many of which are essential workers, would have an even harder time getting around. Their movement is especially important during a pandemic when their help is needed most. Aevaz also pointed out the increased health risk with major cuts to rail services. “I think the overall thing is that the bus network is more widely used than the rail network for essential workers. It is going to be harmful because people will have to wait longer or have to take more crowded buses to work- that’s a health risk in and of itself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many D.C. residents, the proposed service cuts would be a major inconvenience. But for some, these cuts would have far greater implications for their quality of life. TIME Reporter Researcher Alejandro de la Garza wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5869375/public-transit-coronavirus-covid/&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; back in July on the effects of COVID-19 on public transit. I spoke with him about the impact of reduced transit service. “For people who are dependent on public transportation, when you reduce bus service that means there is a much greater chance that when the bus comes it is going to be full, and in the coronavirus pandemic you don’t want to be getting on super crowded buses to begin with,” Garza said. “That’s a whole other hour that you wait, and that’s not an inconvenience. That can really screw up your entire day. When you talk about the effects of those kinds on a person over a long period of time, that can really hurt someone’s quality of life.” If the proposal is to go into effect, we can expect further detriments for captive riders, especially essential workers, and a likely rise in COVID-19 cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of Metro in D.C. and public transport nationwide is riding on federal assistance. The American Public Transportation Association (APTA) is &lt;a href=&quot;https://apta.com/advocacy-legislation-policy/legislative-updates-alerts/updates/urge-members-of-congress-to-support-at-least-32-billion-of-additional-covid-19-emergency-funding-for-public-transit/&quot;&gt;calling&lt;/a&gt; on Congress to provide at least $32 billion in emergency funding for public transit. APTA President and CEO Paul Skoutelas &lt;a href=&quot;https://apta.com/news-publications/press-releases/releases/statement-from-apta-president-and-ceo-paul-p-skoutelas-2/&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; that this funding will help public transit agencies to, “continue to provide essential services through the crisis and play an indispensable role in America’s economic recovery from COVID-19.” The funding would help offset revenue loss and prevent having to lay off large numbers of transit employees. Whether Congress will abide is another story. APTA issued their call for action in July, and the question still looms. “From the people I spoke to, especially the heads of these public transportation authorities, back in July or June, it was kind of inconceivable that they were not gonna get assistance, and then lo and behold we are in November and no assistance has come,” said Garza. The assistance is dependent on whether the Senate can reach a majority decision on a stimulus proposal. Senate Minority Leader Charles E. Schumer (D-N.Y) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/transportation/2020/08/05/key-democrats-pledge-support-more-federal-aid-transit/&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; in a virtual news conference in August that, “27 Senate Republicans don’t want to spend one nickel on this. When you have a great transit crisis and economic crisis the public needs you to do it. Investing in mass transit now means that hard-working families can rely on the subway and bus to earn a living.” Congress is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/transportation/2020/08/05/key-democrats-pledge-support-more-federal-aid-transit/&quot;&gt;expected&lt;/a&gt; to vote on a new relief proposal as early as next week which could abet D.C.’s public transit crisis or aggravate it. In the meantime, D.C. residents should prepare for an unrecognizable transit system in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/metro-ridership-covid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/metro-ridership-covid/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mexico, India, China are Leading Sources of Legal Immigration to the U.S.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The United States, historically touted as the land of opportunity, has received immigrants from a wealth of countries over the years. However, according to an analysis of recent immigration data from the Migration Policy Institute (MPI), the majority of immigrants legally entering the United States over the past two decades has coalesced around the same three countries: Mexico, India and China. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Annual Immigration Rates 1999-2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Z8O6b&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Z8O6b/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;978&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1999, the United States has seen a steady stream of immigrants from these nations, indicating a clear – and virtually consistent pattern – of who comprises the U.S.’s immigration population, and offering us a glimpse into what the nation might look like in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, about 3.5 million Mexican immigrants reside in the United States, followed by nearly 1.4 million Chinese immigrants and 1.3 Indian immigrants. With a yearly average of 155,271 immigrants from Mexico, 64,417 from China and 60,327 from India for the past 21 years, these numbers are slowly changing the racial and ethnic makeup of the United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immigrant Count Breakdown Per Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4545739&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4545792&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4545807&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“While Hispanics are still the largest racial and ethnic minority group, there has been a growing presence of Asian-born immigrants also coming to the United States,” said Gitika Harith, a research intern at MPI. “This research helps us gauge where immigration is most prevalent and understand trends as to why that is - specifically for the top three countries of Mexico, China and India.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various &lt;a href=&quot;https://oxfordre.com/americanhistory/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780199329175.001.0001/acrefore-9780199329175-e-146&quot;&gt;push and pull factors&lt;/a&gt; that determine why a Mexican citizen would choose to immigrate to the U.S. The history of Mexican immigration to the U.S. is best characterized as the movement of unskilled, manual laborers &lt;em&gt;pushed&lt;/em&gt; northward mostly by poverty and &lt;em&gt;pulled&lt;/em&gt; into American labor markets with higher wages. Historically, most Mexicans have been economic immigrants seeking to improve their lives, although many still work in primarily low-skilled jobs. Even amidst four presidencies, coupled with their cabinet’s respective immigration policy priorities and restrictions, Mexico has remained the highest country of origin for immigrants every year for nearly two decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MPI research also contains information regarding citizenship rates from these nations from 1999 to 2019. Coincidentally, the same nations occupy the highest rates of obtained citizenship. Data shows that out of all immigrants seeking citizenship, Mexico dominates the charts with nearly 2.4 million naturalized citizens.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&quot;Annual Naturalization Citizenship Count 1999-2019&quot; aria-label=&quot;chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-b9U2r&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/b9U2r/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;978&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many Mexican immigrants come to the U.S. so that they can provide a better future for their children, even if they themselves would have rather stayed in Mexico,” said Amy Fisher, legislative assistant overseeing immigration affairs in the office of Congresswoman Pramila Jayapal (WA-07). “We have seen a clear attack from the Trump administration on Mexican immigrants in particular, but the reality is Mexican immigrants actually make up the bulk of our &lt;em&gt;legal&lt;/em&gt; immigrants, many of which later go on to pursue the arduous and costly naturalization process.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mexican Naturalization Rates Per Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4545973&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MPI, Mexican immigrants occupy the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/asian-immigrants-united-states-2014&quot;&gt;greatest number of B-1 and B-2 visas&lt;/a&gt;, which are far easier to acquire than HB1s or green cards. These visas (B-1 or B-2) are primarily given to supply the kinds of low-wage jobs that many immigrants from Mexico and other Latin American countries are employed with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, the high levels of Asian immigrants are primarily attributed to their employment in high-skilled jobs and pursuit of higher education. Immigration from Asia to the United States &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/asian-immigrants-united-states-2014&quot;&gt;rose dramatically with passage of the 1965 Immigration and Nationality Act&lt;/a&gt;, which removed the 1921 national-origin quotas restricting immigration from Asian and Arab countries and sharply limiting arrivals from Africa, eastern and southern Europe. The Act also prioritized highly educated and skilled workers arriving on H-1B visas. Since then, Asian Americans have comprised a large segment of the United States immigration population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, the top two origin countries of Asian immigrants and naturalized citizens are India and China. The migration motivations and demographic characteristics of Asian immigrants have varied greatly over time and by country of origin - ranging from employment and family reunification to educational opportunities and humanitarian protection. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indian and Chinese Naturalization Rates Per Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4545984&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4546012&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramon Saldanha, who immigrated to the United States from India in 1988, explains that the driving force behind his decision was simple: to get an education. “The only reason I was able to come to the United States is because I was accepted to grad school at the University of Detroit. I came on a student visa and was lucky that United States Steel was then willing to sponsor me for employment,” said Saldanha. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reality is not isolated to him, and certainly does not surprise demographers or immigration lawyers, who say that unlike Mexican immigrants, that path to citizenship for Asian immigrants is much easier as a result of company sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“High skilled employment opportunities in the United States continue to grow for people in Asian countries, mostly for high-tech and engineering, since the U.S. has a lack of employers in these fields” said corporate immigration lawyer Kane Vongsavanh of Berry Appleman and Lediden Law Firm, “Most of my corporate clients outsource to Indian and Chinese immigrants, many of which do come here to study in graduate schools and just wind up staying here.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these trends are staggering, the numbers can evolve over time, especially given the Trump administration’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/10/06/politics/trump-visa-restrictions/index.html&quot;&gt;rollback on H-1B visas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/immigration/trump-immigration-walls/2020/10/31/e43453cc-09a3-11eb-991c-be6ead8c4018_story.html&quot;&gt;restrictions on Mexican immigrants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The long-term effect of policies usually takes a few years,” Harith said. “It is likely that we will only see the effects of the Trump administration’s policies in our immigration numbers within the next 5 years.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it is evident that these trends have sustained and arguably, thrived, over the past two decades – sending us a clear message of not just who we are, but what we are becoming.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/immigration/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/immigration/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mission and Tenderloin District remain to be San Francisco’s Crime Hot Spots</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2018, The San Francisco Police department has had a decrease of incidents reported within its 36 different neighborhoods. Despite its 34% decrease in cases, two neighborhoods still remain to have the highest amount of cases - The Mission and Tenderloin district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 2018 and 2020 The Mission District, located east central of San Francisco, had decreased their number of incident reports by 7,524.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founded in 1776, the Mission District was the first the neighborhood to be settled in San Francisco by European missionaries, penning its name. Today, the Mission District is home to a large Hispanic community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Mission is home to a diverse and rich history, it is San Francisco’s most dangerous neighborhood with a total of 405,024 incidents reports as of 2020.  With 124,013 of cases being larceny and theft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Mission district, the tenderloin District remained to have highest amount of incident reports in both 2018 and 2020. With only decreasing their cases by 33%, between 2018-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Located in downtown San Francisco, the Tenderloin district has been a safe haven for outcasts since its founding. With many of its community being refugees from the Vietnam war. Since then Tenderloin has become a beacon of goodwill in the bay area, provided by nonprofit organizations that have created housing and community aid. Similar to Mission, Tenderloins top category of incidents is of Larceny and theft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, another pattern found in the incident reports by the San Francisco police department was the Intersections where the incidents occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Tenderloins district Top incident intersection was 8TH ST/ Grove ST/ Hyde ST/ Market ST with 637 reports, With most of the incidents reported being related to Drug offenses. However, in 2020 that changed with Golden Gate AVE / Hyde ST, taking the top spot with 560 Reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being That the Tenderloin District has become notorious with its growing Illegal drug Market, its high number in drug offense reports is no surprise. Most of the drugs being sold in the district include heroin, Meth, Fentanyl and Cocaine. In fact, 8th ST/ Grove ST/ Hyde ST/ Market ST had the highest amount of drug offenses because the intersection is an entrance to The Civic Center Station, which has garnered the attention of drug dealers as market spot. Similarly, in 2020 that market spot moved to Golden Gate AVE/ Hyde ST, where just as September a Tenderloin Drug Dealer was accused of Trafficking Fentanyl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the Mission District, most incidents reports from 2018 came from the 16th ST/ Mission ST intersection, most of which were larceny theft.  However, In 2020 16th ST/ Mission remained at the top spot for most incidents, even though they had a decrease in crime reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16th ST/Mission ST, also known as BART station, gained the reputation of being the most dangerous area in mission district. Gaining reports of Theft, Rape, Assault, and even shootings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent event of crime in Mission was just a week ago, that involved the police and a man engaging in a deadly alteration; which left the man in a life-threatening condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there has been a decrease in crime within the Bay area Community from 2018. Crime still remains to be prevalent issue in San Francisco.  Despite the global pandemic the SF area still faced high rates of crimes, specifically after lockdown ended in March. Between May to August 2020, SF experienced a surge of crime, especially Burglary, Arson and Homicide. But due to the recent political climate and rise in the BLM movement, The San Francisco Police has been under fire for its failure to report and put an end to crimes. 
The San Francisco Police Media Relations Unit had nothing to comment on the crime rates found in Mission and Tenderloin , and any future plans to further decrease crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One Organization that has been taking matter into their own hands has been STOP CRIME SF, which focuses on reducing and preventing crime in San Francisco. In August 2020 Frank Noto, president of STOP CRIME SF, said in a press release following the rise in cases over the summer that the increase in crime could be blamed on San Francisco District attorney Chesa Boudin. Who during his time in office has failed to prosecute many criminals that hold charges of burglary, murder, and drug possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of Boudins failure to solve crime in San Francisco is the case of Delvon Carter and Jared Wilson. According to the San Francisco Chronicle, in early 2020 Delvon Carter, 21, and Jared Wilson, 31, were arrested for multiple accounts of Auto burglary that spanned across the bay area. Additionally, Carter and Wilson had multiple accounts of stolen property from a total of 18 victims. Following the arrest Wilson was released on bail and Carter was offered probation and only two days in jail. Along with their failure to properly convict the pair, The Police department overlooked Carter’s previous arrest record.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:49:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/san-francisco-crime/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/san-francisco-crime/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2020 Election Turnout Was The Highest in 120 Years, But Why?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In most American elections, between 35 and 60 percent of eligible voters will not cast a ballot, however, this year’s turnout broke a nearly century long record. More Americans voted in the 2020 presidential election than any other election in 120 years. Even amidst a   consequential pandemic, approximately 159 million people voted according to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.electproject.org/&quot;&gt;United States Election Project&lt;/a&gt;, a turnout-tracking database run by University of Florida professor Michael McDonald.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;2020 voter turnout compared to other presidential elections&quot; aria-label=&quot;chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-bImgG&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/bImgG/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;600&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite American elections having a tendency for low turnout, this year was already anticipated to have high numbers of people showing up to the polls. Data Reporter for FiveThirtyEight, Nathaniel Rakich notes that the 2018 midterm elections were a key indicator of a change brewing in the American voter base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the 2018 House [of Representatives] and Senate elections, there was a huge turnout that normally you don’t see in non-presidential elections,” Rakich said. “I do think 2020 was on pace to having a high turnout ever since Donald Trump’s election. There was a lot of energy from the Democrat party to get out the vote, and they were able to flip the House as a result.” In fact, according to the United States Election Project, 50 % of the voting eligible population voted in the 2018 midterm elections, the highest turnout since 1914.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With much anticipation for this presidential election, there were a lot of factors that could have contributed to this high turnout. As noted by Rakich, Donald Trump’s presidency increased political activism amongst Americans, especially those who typically vote Democrat. However, within the last year of Trump’s term, the American public has had to endure a fatal and economically damaging pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the infamous police killing of George Floyd led to a resurgence of the Black Lives Matter movement across the nation. This rendered unique circumstances to this election, with tensions high over racial injustice and COVID-19 frustrations. Not only was the 2020 political climate vastly different from election years prior, but the pandemic also caused the election to be conducted in an unusual manner so as to maintain social distancing and safety measures. Furthermore, COVID-19 had ranging effects on voters throughout the election, originally sparking concerns about voter turnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A data report from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://electioninnovation.org/new-voter-registrations-in-2020/&quot;&gt;Center for Election Innovation and Research&lt;/a&gt; tracked voter registration trends in eleven states and the District of Columbia, finding that the pandemic had damaging effects on registering new voters. Initially, looking at voter registration data in the first months of the pandemic, there was a large drop in new registrations comparatively to 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Voter Registration Dropped In The Beginning of the Pandemic&quot; aria-label=&quot;Grouped Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Jav4f&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Jav4f/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;969&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
      &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the first months of the pandemic, there was lots of job loss, city-wide closures, and efforts to stop the spread of the virus. This vast societal change could have had something to do with low registration numbers. However, in many of these states, in the months following George Floyd’s death and the Black Lives Matter movement, there was a stark increase in voter registrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Voter Registration Rises After George Floyd Protests&quot; aria-label=&quot;Grouped Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-yJdIP&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/yJdIP/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;898&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;2016 vs 2020 Voter Registration&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-PjSIQ&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/PjSIQ/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Dalbec, the managing director of APCO Worldwide, an independent public affairs and research agency, worked with polling data for the 2020 election and found that these numbers were significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think a couple factors contribute to the high turnout we saw in 2020, but the aftermath of George Floyd’s death and others over the summer really started a serious conversation about social and racial inequity,” Dalbec said. “People were really motivated to vote or to at least be politically active after Black Lives Matter protests and we can even see a change in our political climate afterwards.” As voter registration progressively increased after June and July, indicating the Black Lives Matter movement’s influence on voter turnout, efforts amongst states to allow for early voting or vote by mail began. Rakich believes that the pandemic, originally thought to thwart turnout, may have actually helped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The pandemic clearly wasn’t fatal to the turnout this year, even though there was uncertainty about navigating this election through COVID-19,” Rakich stated, citing concerns about accessibility to vote. “Kind of paradoxically, by forcing many states to switch to vote by mail, which has historically increased voter turnout, you could say that pandemic increased turnout. At the very least, we can be confident that it didn’t have a significant dampening effect.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the United States Election Project reports that there were about 100 million early ballots, 65 million of which were mail-in ballots. It is likely that more people voted by mail because of concerns about contracting the COVID-19 virus and especially because more states allowed for no excuse absentee voting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because of the pandemic, states made it easier to request mail-in ballots.  There were 5 states that still required voters to provide an excuse to vote absentee ballots, but 45 states let people vote by mail if they wanted to. In normal elections, only 34 states plus Washington DC allow for no excuse absentee voting,” Rakich stated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thalia Tossetti, first time voter and mail-in ballot voter from New York also believes that the pandemic made voting easier for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This election more people are probably voting, because for me, in New York, it’s easier to request and mail absentee ballots and I know you can also vote early,” Tossetti said. “Honestly, COVID-19 made it more accessible to vote. I wanted to vote absentee because I wouldn’t be home for the election, but in my state, you didn’t even need an excuse to vote by mail.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While America has had turnout rise and fall throughout history, this election comes at time with unprecedented conditions. With the pandemic’s abysmal effect on the economy, Donald Trump’s presidency inspiring many left-leaning voters to show up to the polls, as well as the impassioned energy surrounding the Black Lives Matter movement, the American environment was ripe for change. Yet, because of the uniqueness of this election, these voter trends may not continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I had to guess, I would say this election is an anomaly,” Rakich said conclusively. “Overall 2024 might look more like 2016. That said, every new trend starts with one data point, and maybe this will be the start of a high voter turnout trend.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:49:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/election-turnout/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/election-turnout/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time for a new bike lock? DC bike thefts are up 28% since last year</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Daniel Matos would like to ride his bike to work tomorrow morning, but it was stolen from outside his apartment on November 21. He’s not the only one, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bike thefts in the district area are up 28% since last year, likely as a direct result of nationwide bike shortages due to high demand and limited supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot; src=&quot;https://www.datawrapper.de/_/qADUP/ &quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;428&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:677.0208339999999,&quot;200&quot;:514.0208339999999,&quot;300&quot;:470.020834,&quot;400&quot;:470.020834,&quot;500&quot;:444.020834,&quot;700&quot;:428.020834,&quot;800&quot;:428.020834,&quot;900&quot;:428.020834,&quot;1000&quot;:428.020834},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;Oha3H&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matos had been riding to work instead rather than taking public transportation and risk a coronavirus infection. “I don’t want to take the Metro or a bus every day. That’s too much exposure,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay Crockett, who works at multiple locations of Conte’s bike shop, said he’s noticed an uptick in bike thefts in the greater Washington area. He theorized that this was the result of the shortage of new bikes. But the bikes he does have in stock aren’t exactly affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buyers-rejoice&quot;&gt;Buyers rejoice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The walls of Conte’s bike shop in Cathedral heights are laced with intimidating Italian road racing bikes commanding prices of $7,000 and up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crockett said most riders who would normally be looking under the $3,000 range (generally not commuters) are now “starting to explore things that are up there a little bit further in price around $3,000 to 6,000 range.” It’s an expensive hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npd.com/wps/portal/npd/us/news/press-releases/2020/cycling-industry-sales-growth-accelerates-in-april/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; by the NPD group, which analyzes consumer data, total April bicycle sales hit $1 billion, compared to a typical April average of $550 and $575 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the resale market has exploded, with parts and complete bikes sometimes selling more than what they were worth new on sites like Craigslist and Facebook Marketplace, Crockett said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s hard to say whether the pandemic’s effects on bike sales have been more of a blessing or a curse for shops. On the one hand, everyone wants a bike, but on the other, there are none left and they’ve all been sold out since April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is with suppliers. Michael Button, an employee of popular bike manufacturer Specialized, said, globally, bike supply has fallen far behind. “Factories have shut down, and they were never made to handle this much off-season demand anyway,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every shop in the nation, everybody in North America, everybody in the global market, everybody’s sort of doing the same thing of trying to get parts, sourcing them from places that are traditionally unconventional,” said Crockett. “The industry as a whole hasn’t seen a surge in sales and service traffic like this since probably the early 2010s.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’ve still got bikes on the way, they’re just coming a little later,” Button said. “2021 models will likely be on the shelves alongside discounted 2020 models that didn’t make it in time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While sales are lagging behind, as of November, which is late in the season, bike shops like Conte’s have mostly been seeing service take the largest share of their revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The floor of the shop is filled with used bikes waiting for repair. Turnaround time was often multiple few weeks in the summer time, according to another Conte’s employee’s estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buyers-remorse&quot;&gt;Buyers’ remorse&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With bikes supplies low and sale prices high, bicycle thieves have upgraded their methods. “We’re starting to see a lot of angle-grinder stuff,” Crockett said, referring to thieves’ use of high powered saws to free bikes of their locks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I went outside Monday morning to find my bike missing. They cut through the lock, there was nothing left except for the lock,” said Matos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matos bought the bike a few years ago and he’s not ready to give it up. He’s reported the theft bike to sites like bikeindex.org and Facebook lost and found groups in the hopes that someone will spot his ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you live in Adams Morgan, Shaw or in the downtown area be on high alert. Your new (or old) bike might be stolen. Property thefts from these neighborhoods saw the most bike thefts in August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot; src=&quot;https://www.datawrapper.de/_/2L2Ha/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;428&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:677.0208339999999,&quot;200&quot;:514.0208339999999,&quot;300&quot;:470.020834,&quot;400&quot;:470.020834,&quot;500&quot;:444.020834,&quot;700&quot;:428.020834,&quot;800&quot;:428.020834,&quot;900&quot;:428.020834,&quot;1000&quot;:428.020834},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;Oha3H&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crockett, from Conte’s bike shop, also manages several Washington-local bike recovery pages online. “The amount of people requesting the join some of these groups on Facebook… it’s just out of the water, I’m getting probably 10 to 15 requests a day,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He estimates an increase in thefts anywhere from 58% to 63%, although analysis of the data from bikeindex.org suggests a more modest increase of 28% since 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tips-on-finding-and-keeping-a-bike&quot;&gt;Tips on finding (and keeping) a bike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crockett said that, while Conte’s shelves are starting to fill up again, the best place to buy a bike is still likely secondhand, through Facebook Marketplace or Craigslist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He recommended inspecting a bike thoroughly before buying it ─ you don’t want to get home and find that catastrophic damage renders the bike useless. 
Be careful what color you pick, too. Buying a black or gray bike might not be the best idea, given the frequency of which they are stolen, according to bikeindex.org data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot; src=&quot;https://www.datawrapper.de/_/d5o8a/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important;&quot; height=&quot;428&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;if(&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper)window.datawrapper={};window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:677.0208339999999,&quot;200&quot;:514.0208339999999,&quot;300&quot;:470.020834,&quot;400&quot;:470.020834,&quot;500&quot;:444.020834,&quot;700&quot;:428.020834,&quot;800&quot;:428.020834,&quot;900&quot;:428.020834,&quot;1000&quot;:428.020834},window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-Oha3H&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])if(&quot;Oha3H&quot;==b)window.datawrapper[&quot;Oha3H&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for keeping your new bike safe, it’s best to keep it inside if possible. Otherwise, making sure to lock it properly is important. “You want to lock the wheels to the frame and the frame to the bike rack or something that’s not going anywhere,” Crockett said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crockett said thieves are “seeing people come home with new bikes, flashy bikes,” and taking the opportunity to steal them. He recounted one story of a high-end $12,000 bike stolen from a supposedly secure bike locker in an apartment in the district recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Metropolitan Police Department, who rejected a request for comment, recommends locking your bike in a secure location, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mpdc.dc.gov/page/bicycle-registration-district-columbia&quot;&gt;registering&lt;/a&gt; your bike and calling 911 as soon as your bike is stolen. You can visit their &lt;a href=&quot;https://mpdc.dc.gov/page/bikes-and-helmet-safety&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; for more tips and riding safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miracles do happen, of course. A woman from the Netherlands “had her bike stolen here in DC when she was traveling,” said Crockett, and a local bike shop found it and “were more than happy to cover the cost of shipping and back to her,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, Matos will find the same luck.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:49:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/bicycle-theft-dc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/bicycle-theft-dc/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The approval rating of Trump’s handling of the Covid-19 pandemic went down as cases went up, but did it matter in the election?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The United States is now nearing 14 million coronavirus cases, with over 270,000 deaths, and cases are continuing to rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Total Covid-19 Cases in the United States 2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-g94m9&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/g94m9/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past nine months, all eyes have been on the Trump administration as economic effects and individual state mandates have caused the pandemic to become an increasingly polarized issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic, President Trump’s average approval rating of his handling of the pandemic dropped six percentage points across all parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Average Approval Rating of Trump's Handling of Covid-19&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-gwBUj&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/gwBUj/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The severity of the pandemic became a key issue in the 2020 Presidential election, and some argue that Trump’s handling of the pandemic played a role in his loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a very different election because of Covid, not just as an issue, but as something that has fundamentally changed the mechanics of the election,” said Dhrumil Mehta, a data journalist at FiveThirtyEight that created the data tracking the approval rating of Trump’s handling of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic was not only a huge topic in the election, but also lead to more mail-in and early voting, changing how the election process was conducted altogether, said Mehta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though many did not approve of Trump’s handling of the pandemic, it is unclear whether he really lost many of his loyal supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The polls have shown that citizens have become less satisfied with Trump’s handling of the pandemic over the past few months as cases have risen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Relationship Between Covid-19 Cases and Trump's Approval Rating of his Handling of the Pandemic &quot; aria-label=&quot;chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-q7GvN&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/q7GvN/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Relationship Between Covid-19 Cases and Trump's Disapproval Rating of his Handling of the Pandemic&quot; aria-label=&quot;chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-dqY0J&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/dqY0J/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though his overall approval rating has remained relatively consistent, Trump’s approval rating of how he handled the pandemic has decreased by six percentage points and his disapproval rating of his handling of the coronavirus has increased by 10 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Malloy, an analyst for the Quinnipiac University poll, said the polls act as a reflection of what the public is concerned about and seeing the drop in approval rating of Trump’s handling of the pandemic was significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That was important, it wasn’t just the experts telling us this, it was other Americans telling us to be concerned, and people tend to listen to their fellow Americans,” said Malloy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the total average approval rating dropped, when the data is broken down between democrats and republicans, the ratings are very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By November, the approval rating for Trump’s handling of the pandemic among democrats was only seven percent, dropping 14 percentage points from earlier this year when it was 21 percent in February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Trump’s approval rating of the pandemic handling among republicans rose 5.6 percent to 86.5 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Average Approval Rating of Trump's Handling of Covid-19 Between Parties
&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-IVfFZ&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/IVfFZ/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows the drastic divide between political parties when it comes to opinions on the pandemic, as many republicans chose to continue to support Trump in the 2020 election. 
 For Nicholas Bicho, 21, a student studying finance, the pandemic made him think harder about who he was going to vote for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think I would have definitely been more clearly Trump if the pandemic didn’t happen … even though I did ultimately vote for Trump,” said Bicho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Bicho stated that he was concerned about the pandemic and wanted a mask mandate, he did approve of many of the measures that the Trump administration put in place, such as the stimulus package and closing the border between China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the change in approval rating, Trump’s disapproval rating of his handling of the pandemic also went up 10.5 percent between the months of March and November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among democrats, Trump’s average disapproval rating of his handling of the pandemic jumped from 56 percent to 92.5 percent, resulting in a 36 percentage point increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among republicans, his disapproval rating rose 4.6 percentage points, from 7.9 percent in February to 12.5 percent in November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Average Disapproval Rating of Trump's Handling of Covid-19 Between Parties
&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-M8w56&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/M8w56/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could relate to how Trump spoke about the coronavirus to his supporters, by putting emphasis on the economy instead of the virus itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Trump very much framed it as the economy versus controlling the virus, and he chose the economy,” said Peter Aldhous, a science reporter at Buzzfeed News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this, many republicans were more concerned about the unemployment rate and the failing economy than the virus itself, causing a divide between parties on how they wanted the virus to be handled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is this dichotomy between democrats and republicans. If you have the virus under control, you can run the economy and do both, but that was not the narrative that was formed in the media and among politicians,” said Mehta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the approval and disapproval ratings of the Trump administration’s handling of the coronavirus have changed throughout the year, so has the general concern about the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January to November, the number of Americans that said they were very concerned about the coronavirus went up 23 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of Americans who said they were somewhat concerned has dropped 3.5 percentage points over the course of the year, resulting in 33 percent of Americans identifying as somewhat concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The percent of not very concerned Americans went down 10 percentage points over the course of the year, along with 10.5 percent of Americans saying that they were not at all concerned about the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4626225&quot;&amp;gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the general concern about the coronavirus has fluctuated over the year, it has remained somewhat steady throughout recent months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As it’s progressed, I see it now as more concerning thing because of the way that case levels have risen, but I personally feel less anxious about it,” said Meredith Goyette, 19. 
 “I think this is in the American consciousness right now, we’ve really just kind of normalized living with it, said Goyette, a student at American University who has been continuing her studies online as a result of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though both Trump’s approval rating and disapproval rating of his handling of the pandemic correlated with the rise in coronavirus cases, Trump was still able to maintain support, even in southern states where the number of cases was high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It doesn’t look, especially at the local level, like Trump was being specifically punished for his response to Covid-19,” said Aldhous, who studied how Trump lost few votes in the counties where more people died of Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with poor approval ratings, Trump was able to maintain his loyal supporters and receive over 70 million votes in the 2020 election. This could be because Trump repeatedly told his supporters that the coronavirus was not something to fear, even going as to far as to spread misinformation and call it a hoax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If we had from the beginning not focused on downplaying the virus. I feel like if we hadn’t had the tension, we might have been much better off,” said Dr. Jolynn Gardner, Director of the Public Health Program at American University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, as cases continue to rise, people are looking to see how the Biden administration will handle the coronavirus pandemic differently, while also looking at how we can better prepare as a society in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That might be the lesson in the debate that goes on, is that what do we as a nation do when this next one comes out?” said Anastasia Snelling, Chair of the Department of Health Studies at American University. “If we do value people’s health, what are the strategies that we’re going to use to avoid having a health issue politicized?”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:48:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/polls-and-covid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/polls-and-covid/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Domestic Abuse in DC during the Coronavirus: An Epidemic Within a Pandemic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“I had a hamburger for lunch today”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a casual response, but for domestic abuse survivors, this sentence could save their life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentence has been translated to “my abuser is in the next room.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code words and discretion are the realities of domestic abuse survivors.
Sex abuse cases are decreasing in DC during the Coronavirus pandemic in comparison to years prior. Although this seems to be an improvement, the focus of the pandemic has made domestic violence less of a priority. The decrease in calls to Child Protective Services to report sexual abuse this year shows how abuse isn’t noticed as often when everyone is quarantined at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest numbers of focus currently are reported in Coronavirus cases. As of October 2, DC has had 15,186 positive cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Coronavirus cases rise, domestic abuse cases continue to show a decrease in comparison to previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Sex Abuse Cases in DC Over the Past Decade&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-mHGSi&quot; src=&quot;https://urldefense.com/v3/__https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/mHGSi/2/__;!!IaT_gp1N!ivLKaEunSaEYpeXHvYU3sRhaNvCLz1udRn-Wyr8jU8xQRRxX7Hjow7XYENXKDgU$ &quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual abuse crimes are at the lowest they have been in the past nine years. A total of 143 cases have been reported this year so far.
“The statistics very rarely tell the whole story,” said Thompson.
Because of school shutdowns, working from home, and staying away from others in general, indicating domestic abuse is not as easy as it was once before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a whole constellation of people that often observe and report violent behavior. And right now, most of those people are cut off from the children of the survivors that they regularly see,” said Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sex abuse rate from January to October in 2019 was 2.5 cases per 10,000 residents. The rate in those same months in 2020 is lower with 2 cases per 10,000 residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the Coronavirus, social work appointments are done virtually. This prevents social workers from indicating whether or not a crime has been committed. With fewer crimes being detected from virtual meetings, fewer crimes have been reported this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We know more abuse is going on and once quarantines start to lift and once things open up again, we expect a huge influx of calls to all of those people,” said Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quarantine has kept everyone inside of their homes for abnormal amounts of time. This includes survivors being kept inside with their abusers and limiting opportunities to have time away from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because of COVID, abuse has gone up, not down,” said Thompson. The data provided makes domestic abuse problems show improvement when there is actually a larger problem than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has made the public’s primary goal health and safety of one another. However, the safety and health of survivors have fallen through the cracks, especially in Ward 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the smallest population in DC, Ward 8 has one of the highest sex abuse rates out of any other ward. For every five cases in 2020, Ward 8 was responsible for two of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Sex Abuse Crimes Per 10,000 Residents in DC&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-CFGEl&quot; src=&quot;https://urldefense.com/v3/__https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/CFGEl/6/__;!!IaT_gp1N!ivLKaEunSaEYpeXHvYU3sRhaNvCLz1udRn-Wyr8jU8xQRRxX7Hjow7XYWey1Do4$ &quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;802&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Ward 4 has the highest number of Coronavirus cases, holding 10 out of 50 cases, Ward 7 and 8 combined make up 13 out of 50 cases in DC.
The community that makes up Ward 8 faces economic challenges, which tends to lead to more violence, said Sloan Thompson, who works at the DC Coalition Against Domestic Violence as the training and outreach coordinator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ward 8, has consistently had a higher amount of reported domestic violence incidents,” said Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Ward 8 has shown the highest reports of sex abuse in DC, they have the lowest access to domestic shelters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Shelters in DC&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-McH1E&quot; src=&quot;https://urldefense.com/v3/__https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/McH1E/2/__;!!IaT_gp1N!ivLKaEunSaEYpeXHvYU3sRhaNvCLz1udRn-Wyr8jU8xQRRxX7Hjow7XYfZAvjBk$ &quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;748&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the prior map, the amount of accessible shelters for Ward 8 survivors is low. There are three shelters in Ward 8 where the sex abuse rate is 7.85 cases per 10,000 residents. Ward 5 has four shelters and the rates are lower at 5.97 cases per 10,000 residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some victims, choosing to find shelter in a different ward, city, or even state is the safest option for them. This could explain why there is a shortage of housing in Ward 8 for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, some victims cannot afford to move significantly far away due to the commitments that they have in their community. This could include their job or their child’s school, said Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The District Alliance for Safe Housing (DASH) works to provide housing for survivors in areas outside of shelters. Although not every survivor has been housed, the transitional housing that is being offered still helps survivors leave their abuser and claim their life back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work done by the District Alliance for Safe Housing helps to compensate for the lack of domestic shelters. The transitional housing also allows for survivors to have a place to go even when domestic shelters are at max capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DASH has a housing clinic located in DC for survivors to get in contact and find out what their options are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Positive Covid Cases Per 1,000 Residents in DC&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Vyi8E&quot; src=&quot;https://urldefense.com/v3/__https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Vyi8E/6/__;!!IaT_gp1N!ivLKaEunSaEYpeXHvYU3sRhaNvCLz1udRn-Wyr8jU8xQRRxX7Hjow7XYxWpxtAw$ &quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;816&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domestic services within DC and across the nation have been added with an extra form of safety for their survivors since the pandemic has begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeBare worked to ensure that shelters/coalitions knew the protocols to follow in order to adjust to the pandemic and keep others safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That primary focus has been to make sure that all the coalitions have the information they need to manage the ever-changing environment we’re in,” said Deborah DeBare, senior deputy director at the National Network to End Domestic Violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeBare worked to ensure that shelters/coalitions knew the protocols to follow in order to adjust to the pandemic and keep others safe.
The morale of staff was also a concern for DeBare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s really hard to do this kind of work to begin with. But when you’re doing it in an isolated way at home, it can be really stressful,” said DeBare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michelle Gardner is a counselor at the support center for The House of Ruth, a domestic shelter in DC. Gardner works both remotely and in-person during the week currently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gardner holds meetings with her patients over Zoom. Patients are initially evaluated to see whether or not they would be safe with using zoom or needed to come in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The therapy is appealing for many people, but, you know, it’s coming after oftentimes, months, years, a lifetime of abusive relationships,” said Gardner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a time of uncertainty, domestic abuse organizations have turned to what they can control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gardner, DeBare, and Thompson all mentioned the importance of staying educated on the topic and ensuring preventative measures are put in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve always found it really empowering to sort of, you know, do outreach,” said Gardner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outreach and education help both survivors and individuals around them. With all of the free time given due to the pandemic, learning about domestic violence can allow survivors to understand what is happening to them and keep those on the outside informed about what is happening in their community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How can we really change things if people don’t know what’s going on,” said Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:48:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/domestic-violence-dc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/domestic-violence-dc/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Young voters could sway the public opinion on decriminalizing marijuana</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The decriminalization and legalization of marijuana is a key issue for American voters. The most recent election saw major changes to marijuana laws in five states. In particular, young voters showed up in favor of legalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2020 election resulted in Arizona, Montana, New Jersey and South Dakota legalizing recreational marijuana. Earlier this year, Illinois was also added to that list. As of this year, marijuana is fully legal in 16 states, including the District of Columbia. Additionally, 42 states have either decriminalized marijuana, allow medicinal marijuana or both. In seven states, CBD oil is the only legal form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Marijuana laws by state&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-qDmAg&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/qDmAg/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;470&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still a relatively new process in the US, as the first states to legalize recreational marijuana, Colorado and Washington, only passed their laws in 2012. In less than a decade, more research has been done. Public opinion and discourse has also adapted in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young voters in particular have shown an upward trend in support. From 1994 to 2018, support for the legalization of marijuana amongst voters aged 18-34 has increased by almost 50%. To find recent data, Gallup released a poll “Americans’ Support for Legalizing Marijuana Among Demographic Groups,” however their age categories were slightly different than that of AP’s data. Nonetheless, as of 2020, we can assume around 77% of voters in that age category show their support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Support among 18-34 year old voters for marijuana legalization by election year from 1994-2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-glTVv&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/glTVv/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;339&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many states, citizens have to be 21 years or older to purchase marijuana, yet that did not stop eager voters aged 18-20 to vote in favor of these new laws. In an Instagram survey with 115 responses from college aged, 18-22 years old individuals, more than 93% said the federal government should decriminalize marijuana. This was a major difference from the amount of individuals who live in a state where that is the current law, just under 23%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Is marijuana legal/decriminalized in your home state?&quot; aria-label=&quot;Stacked Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-q7hqD&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/q7hqD/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;117&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Do you think the federal government should legalize/decriminalize marijuana at a national level?&quot; aria-label=&quot;Stacked Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-GrYIt&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/GrYIt/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;142&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American University sophomore Joe Smieya voted in favor of recreational marijuana in New Jersey this past election. Although Smieya is only 19, he is excited to have the ability to legally use marijuana back home, once he is of age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, Smieya, and many others, understand the complexities of this issue and see it for more than an opportunity to get high. Smieya believes that these new laws are helpful, but not enough to end the stigma around marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Decriminalization is not enough in a lot of ways. Marijuana still suffers from the inherent harms of prohibition. There is unequal advocacy of laws for certain groups of people. These unequal applications are typically against POC and it harms them more than anyone else,” said Smieya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Racial injustice became increasingly discussed in 2020 after the George Floyd protests this summer. When it comes to the decriminalization of marijuana, one can look at the racial components of the war on drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlas Klus, a 19-year-old American University student, also voted in favor of marijuana’s legalization in New Jersey. However, their focus was on protecting BIPOC rather than a personal desire to smoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“POC are prosecuted much more harshly and more often for marijuana related crimes and yet almost every young white boy I know smokes and they never get caught,” said Klus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure the legalization process is both beneficial and equitable has been a balancing act for Virginian legislatures. Their Governor Ralph Northam has made a commitment to legalizing recreational marijuana in 2021. For Illinois cannabis legalization expert Toi Hutchinson, it is of extreme importance that marijuana legalization not only uplift black communities through the legislation process, but through recognizing its social implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to NBC 12, on Wednesday this week, Hutchinson joined the “Legalize It” virtual series run by the Tom Tom Foundation. There, she spoke more to addressing the issue of the criminalization of marijuana, particularly among young, black Virginians, and the implications of Governor Northam’s 2021 promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is one of the first ways, you get introduced, especially young African American boys between 18 and 24, introduced into the criminal justice system. And that has impacts for the rest of their lives for all of these families, for blocks and blocks of people,” said Hutchinson. “Equity in this space is about taking communities who have been harmed and giving them what they need to be in a position to be treated equally.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of government involvement in this issue varies depending on who you ask. However, with public approval rising, as about two thirds of Americans support the legalization of marijuana, pressure is put on politicians to take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the new Biden and Harris administration entering the white house, young voters expressed hope that they would be the team to tackle this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same 115 person survey, around 56% believe that a Biden presidency will lead to the decriminalization of marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Do you think the Biden &amp;amp; Harris administration will legalize/decriminalize marijuana?&quot; aria-label=&quot;Stacked Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-UFVJp&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/UFVJp/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;142&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although a majority of those surveyed expressed hope in the new administration, others shared fears and frustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They [Joe Biden and Kamala Harris] are a bunch of party democrats without a backbone between them,” said 21-year-old Ohioan Benjamin Mooney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as what the public knows about their stances on the issue, Harris has been said to be in favor of legalizing marijuana while Biden has expressed a desire to leave it up to individual states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Although I would like to believe this administration will be progressive enough to legalize marijuana, Kamala’s past does not make me confident,” said 18-year-old University of South Carolina student Sophia Troutman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troutman is referring to Harris’ past as a prosecutor in California where she convicted a high number of residents. She also did not show support for the state’s push for legalization in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there are mixed opinions on the likelihood of major change in the next four years, public approval on the issue seems to be heading in a positive direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new Gallup poll demonstrated a record high of 68% approval amongst Americans in regard to the legalization of marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthew Matos, a 22-year-old account coordinator for CGI health and New Jersey resident expressed that public approval will continue to go up as long as there is more conversation to end the stigma around marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course If you’re relying on weed too much or using it to cope with anything it can be dangerous. However, I think more people need to look into its medical benefits,” said Matos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matos explained that many can overgeneralize the effects of marijuana as they remain ignorant to its complexities. It comes in different strands that give the body different effects that range from increased appetite, pain reduction, relieving anxiety, a feeling of euphoria or even arousal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He walked through the process of the psychoactive component of tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) and how that is used to attach to endocannabinoids in one’s brain, and eventually cannabinoid receptors to give one’s body the feeling of being high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think if you really want to end stigmas about it you have to let people know that although marijuana is a drug, all it is doing is activating something that is already existing in your body,” said Matos.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:48:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/decriminalizie-marijuana/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/decriminalizie-marijuana/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Student Debt is Worse Than Ever Before</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Angelina Floyd’s dream was to study Law in Washington D.C. Little did she know she would be paying for it for the next 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last 10 years, student debt has steadily increased. But as of 2019, the average student’s debt is over $25,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Average Students Debt &quot; aria-label=&quot;chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-BmhwU&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/BmhwU/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;304&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The cost of my happiness and success is over $200,000 it’s scary,” said Floyd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floyd, an American University student, is currently studying justice and law and will owe over $40,000 just from undergraduate education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She plans to continue her education by going to law school, her dream is to go to Georgetown Law. A University that will cost over $60,000 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the burden of the heavy debts, that will potentially take over 20 years to pay off, Floyd wants to continue her dream of becoming a lawyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-scatter&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/4543147&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;debts-lasting-effects&quot;&gt;Debt’s Lasting Effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cody Hounanian, project director at Student Debt Crisis explains the “domino effect” of student loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When graduates have so much debt it limits them from purchasing homes, starting a family, creating small businesses, and even starting credit cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more debt you have the harder it is to start your own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High paying jobs such as a doctor require higher education which requires loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floyd is an example of this. She will be in school until her late 20s raking up thousands of dollars in debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floyd, however, is not worried about paying off her debts believing that once she starts in the workplace she will make a higher salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, the median salary of a student out of law school is $88,000. This means that Floyd could be paying off her debt for over 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lawyers aren’t the only profession that requires higher levels of education. Hounanian said jobs like social workers, teachers, and healthcare workers all require master’s degrees or higher. These professions do not make enough to sustain these loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the pandemic, these industries have also been hit the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floyd is one of many students who dream of receiving higher education at prestigious universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many students have to consider these factors now when applying to college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;money-plays-a-factor-in-decided-on-college&quot;&gt;Money Plays a Factor in Decided on College&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eli Roegge, a High School student, has to think about these factors when applying to college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roegge’s dream is to attend college to study music composition at the University of California Berkley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Roegge can not afford private school tuition forcing him to only apply to public schools in his home state of North Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even attending a public university Roegge still anticipates taking out smaller loans to afford the tuition, that he expects will take him over five years to pay off fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year, more students make their higher education choices based on their economic needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Tuition Per State&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-uUyBm&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/uUyBm/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;502&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These high tuition rates lead to other factors in our society. They perpetuate the racial and economic inequalities in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Black student loan borrowers have less wealth than their peers due to the compounded problem of the wage gap and student debt,” said Hounanian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women are also subjected to this because of the wage gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-being-done&quot;&gt;What’s Being Done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student Debt Crisis, SDC, is a grassroots advocacy organization that is looking to help end student debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SDC has recently switched there focus to help families that are struggling during the pandemic. This includes people who have decreasing working hours or have a job that puts them at an increased risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During COVID-19 the burden of student loans are even more taxing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SDC has received over 1.4 million signatures on a petition to cancel student debt. Hounanian said that the only way to truly fix this problem is to cancel student debt and start making public universities free tuition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things that help students suffering from mass student loan debt are policies such as federal loan refinancing and bankruptcy discharge. Student loan refinancing is receiving a lower interest rate compared to the one you are giving on your federal loans. A bankruptcy discharge is a court order that releases the debtor from paying their debts that are still owed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SDC cosponsored the California Student Borrower Bill of Rights, which will be effective starting on January 1st. This aims to protect borrowers from loan services abuse that can cause student debt to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year is the first year that SDC has publicly supported a presidential nominee, president-elect Joe Biden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biden is being urged by SDC to go even further than his plan suggests by canceling all student loan debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other politicians such as Elizabeth Warren and Chuck Schumer have acknowledged the major issue of student debt and are calling to help end the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warren, who ran for president in 2020, and Schumer had a plan laid out to cancel student loans that owed over $50,000, which is over 42 million people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biden’s plan is to cancel $10,000 of federal student loan debt as COVID-19 relief. This as Hounanian said is a step in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floyd is feeling more optimistic about her choice in degree after Biden became president-elect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m not as worried about undergraduate payments as I was before. I have less of a burden on me for pursuing more education,” Floyd said.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 13:47:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/student-debt/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2020/fall-2020/student-debt/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
