<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COMM-260 Quant Methods &amp; Data Viz (Spring 2021)</title>
    <description>Final projects from students in Quantitative Methods &amp; Data Visualization at American University Fall 2020.  
</description>
    <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 16:07:11 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 16:07:11 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Incarcerated People Have Disproportionately Low Vaccination Rates. Here’s Why</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;34,500 Texas inmates have tested positive for Covid-19. However, only 2,000 doses have been received for incarcerated people, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://covidprisonproject.com/data/national-overview/&quot;&gt;The Covid Prison Project&lt;/a&gt;. No data suggests that any incarcerated people in Texas have been vaccinated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is imperative to note that some inmates may have been vaccinated at this time. However there is no certainty due to a lack of transparency from correctional facilities in terms of data collection disallows us to say so with certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having the highest number of incarcerated people test positive and die as a result of Covid-19, Texas has been extraordinarily slow in the rollout of vaccines for incarcerated people even though many inmates have been eligible for months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Texas stands out in terms of high death rates coupled with low vaccination rates, it is not the only state falling behind in terms of vaccinating incarcerated people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the country incarcerated people, one of the nation’s most vulnerable and disproportionately affected populations to Covid-19, are not getting vaccinated at the same rate as the American public, or even the staff at correctional facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/5974737&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kathryn M. Nowotny, Co-Lead Investigator and Co-Founder of The Covid Prison Project, attributes the slow and inequitable vaccine distribution among Texas correctional facilities to a devaluation of the lives of incarcerated people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because you are an incarcerated person you are unworthy of medical protection,” said Nowotny about the underlying belief of Texas representatives and administrators in charge of vaccine distribution among incarcerated people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With over 70 million Americans fully vaccinated against Covid-19, many feel as though the country is moving toward normalcy. After all, according to the CDC fully vaccinated people can gather indoors without a mask, travel domestically and internationally, and avoid the 14-day quarantine that typically comes with being exposed to the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is not true for millions of people incarcerated in correctional facilities. For them, Covid-19 continues to wreak havoc by diminishing community health and targeting marginalized individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incarcerated people don’t have control over the ability to activate the use of personal protective equipment, or take a rapid Covid test, or talk to their doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, to receive an email from your local health department and schedule a vaccine at your local CVS is a privilege incarcerated people cannot afford. Vaccines should not be a luxury. They are a basic necessity that must be provided to vulnerable populations in a timely and effective manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alberto Gonzalez, Commission Co-Chair of The National Commission on Covid-19 and Criminal Justice highlighted that vaccines necessary for incarcerated people, as well as staff and visitors, in correctional facilities “should reduce the number of people who become infected with Covid.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vaccination rate within correctional facilities is lower than that of the vaccination rate of the general American population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, according to The National Commission on Covid-19 and Criminal Justice, “on average, the COVID-19 mortality rate within prisons (61.8 deaths per 100,000 people in prison) was double the mortality rate for the general population.” So, why aren’t incarcerated people being vaccinated by the state?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the distinction between the vaccination rate of inmates and the general population can be attributed to the historical and institutional mistreatment of America’s prison population, specifically that their livelihood has been neither valued nor protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The socioeconomic and racial and ethnic makeup of populations in prisons tended to be populations at higher risk of Covid,” said Walsh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was within the state’s power to implement compassionate release in correctional facilities with a high number of Covid-19 cases and overcrowding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decarceration, which includes accelerated release practices, was recommended by &lt;a href=&quot;https://counciloncj.foleon.com/covid19/experience-to-action/recommendation-2/&quot;&gt;The Commission&lt;/a&gt;, stating that “given the significant medical vulnerability of some incarcerated individuals, compassionate release policies should be revised and expanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Reducing population density within prisons is very important in order to provide the space for people to social distance,” said Abby Walsh, Commission Manager of the National Commission on Covid-19 and Criminal Justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, compassionate and medical release due to the increased epidemiological risk of contracting and dying from Covid-19 in prisons (which can likely be attributed to the poor health conditions associated with correctional facilities and the compromised health of many inmates, was never the norm in this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gov. Gregg Abbot, for example, actually signed an emergency &lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.texas.gov/uploads/files/press/EO-GA-13_jails_and_bail_for_COVID-19_IMAGE_03-29-2020.pdf&quot;&gt;order&lt;/a&gt;, to bar the release of inmates accused or convicted of violent crimes that cannot afford bail. However, inmates who could pay bail with cash were free to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an element of the cash bail system, which some argue is unconstitutional as it discriminates against impoverished people of color, criminalizing poverty, and produces wealth-based incarceration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also be attributed to the disproportionate mass incarceration of Black and Brown people, a population now disproportionately affected by Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, “why didn’t we compassionately release if we knew early on that Covid-19 that was gonna hit elderly people and people with compromised health in the worst ways?” said Nowotny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is simple - we as a country and society have failed to recognize the humanity of incarcerated people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gonzalez acknowledged that many incarcerated people, currently at a disproportionate risk of contracting and dying from Covid-19 due to their location in correctional facilities, are actually in need of other rehabilitative measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Some people have mental health problems and they shouldn’t be in prison,” said Gonzalez. “Send them to a mental health facility.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is this a way to show that we recognize the humanity of people who commit crimes, but also a way to reduce population density and control the spread of Covid-19 in prisons, Gonzalez pointed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vulnerable and underprivileged population, people in jails and prisons have never been prioritized in terms of health and safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to public health crises, they have been exploited and experimented upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This neglect for humanity and respect for incarcerated people, especially those who are already included within marginalized communities, continues in terms of the racial disparities associated with Covid-19 in correctional facilities, and the country at large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We know that incarceration impacts people who are also disproportionately impacted by Covid-19, typically poor or low-income communities, Black and Brown communities,” said Walsh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, despite only making up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/US/PST045219&quot;&gt;13.4% of the population&lt;/a&gt;, those who identify as Black or African American make up 15% of the number of people who have died as a result of Covid-19. Additionally, those who identify as Hispanic or Latino who make up approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/US/PST045219&quot;&gt;18.5% of the population&lt;/a&gt; make up 19% of those who have died due to Covid-19 in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/covid-data/investigations-discovery/hospitalization-death-by-race-ethnicity.html&quot;&gt;Center for Disease Control and Prevention&lt;/a&gt;, this translates to Black or African Americans being 1.9 times more likely to die from Covid-19 than white people, and Hispanic or Latino persons 2.3 times more likely to die from Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a more detailed breakdown of Covid-19 deaths by race and ethnicity by state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Vykgs&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Vykgs/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-sKQHv&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/sKQHv/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is imperative to understand that Covid-19 has further exacerbated this inequality. &lt;a href=&quot;https://covid19.counciloncj.org/2020/11/09/impact-report-racial-disparities-and-covid-19-2/&quot;&gt;The Commission&lt;/a&gt; reports that “people of color have experienced higher infection and mortality rates from COVID-19.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For criminal justice and government officials to ignore Covid-19 infection and mortality data surrounding incarcerated people, specifically Black and Brown people, and not prioritize them in terms of vaccine distribution and administration is neglect. It is a refusal to recognize incarcerated people as human beings worthy of protection and compassion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we as a country move forward towards a “new normal” comprising mandatory vaccinations, continued social distancing, and a fundamental shift in the way we live our lives, it is imperative that incarcerated people are not just included but prioritized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must provide correctional facilities the resources to collect and provide data on vaccination distribution in every state, if not to the public to the CDC and Congress, as transparency is key to ensuring incarcerated people are not neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must move to reduce population density within prisons to provide the space for people to social distance, not just during Covid-19, but in future public health crises of this magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must hold politicians accountable when they promise to vaccinate their constituents and provide support to those struggling as a result of Covid-19 - even when those constituents are incarcerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, and integrated into every action we take concerning the physical and mental well-being of incarcerated people, we must demand a recognition of the humanity of incarcerated people and ensure we take the necessary steps to adapt our system so that we are better equipped to deal with the next public health threat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:50:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/incarcerated-covid-vaccinated/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/incarcerated-covid-vaccinated/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evanston's reparations program falls short of community needs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lesley Williams could not stop thinking about her father in the days after March 22, when the city of Evanston, Illinois passed the nation’s first reparations program. She racked her mind — ‘what would he have to say about this?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had faced a lifetime of injustice. When he transferred to Northwestern University, he wasn’t allowed to live in the dorms but rather find housing with a local Black family. Williams, a Black resident of Evanston for over 25 years, was raised in a Chicago bungalow on Michigan and 91st. Redlining &lt;a href=&quot;https://dsl.richmond.edu/panorama/redlining/#loc=13/41.728/-87.666&amp;amp;city=chicago-il&amp;amp;area=D97&quot;&gt;maps&lt;/a&gt; described her childhood neighborhood as “a good neighborhood from a negro standpoint.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Even if my father was still alive, there’s no way that this could actually make up for everything that happened to him and everything that happened to all the other Black people in American history,” Williams said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Williams, residents and others have weighed in — the reparations program set into motion by the city council falls short, undermining past and present racial disparities in the city and presenting an ineffective solution to a long-lasting problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disparities faced by Black residents in Evanston are widespread and extend far beyond the effects of discriminatory housing policies that the city has centralized on with its reparations program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the city’s decade-long reparations program begins to unfold, what does this mean for Black residents that face other types of racial discrimination? What about residents who don’t qualify for reparations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at other factors that historically and presently harm marginalized communities, it was found that Black residents in Evanston are disproportionately arrested and policed. Black students are also disproportionately punished compared to their white peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evanston’s population totals around 74,000 residents. Of that number, 67 percent are white, and 17 percent are Black. Despite being in the minority, Black people make up the majority of arrests recorded by the Evanston Police Department. In fact, a Black person is seven times more likely to be arrested than a white person in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/6038735/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/6038735/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/6038735&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Hispanic residents are included in the white category. Evanston Police Department’s data does not reflect an accurate distinction between the two. Of the 67 percent, 60 percent are white-alone, and the remaining identify as Hispanic or Latinx.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These inequalities were found to leak into police activity as well. The segregated boundaries enforced by the city’s discriminatory policies in the mid-twentieth century remain today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic stop violations recorded by the Evanston Police Department show that neighborhoods with a larger Black population are more heavily policed and ticketed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the map displays, police activity in these neighborhoods was more likely to be internal, meaning that police were active within neighborhood streets rather than on bordering, busy roads — a trend shown in areas with larger white populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/5849659/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/5849659/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/5849659&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Williams, policing has long been an issue disproportionately affecting Evanston’s Black community. In October 2015, Lawrence Crosby, a graduate student at Northwestern University, was beaten by police after a passerby mistook him for stealing the car he owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you really wanted to show that you cared about African American residents, you might consider defunding the police and using some of that money to support African American communities,” Williams said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to policing, data from Evanston Township High School’s Board of Education, the city’s only public high school, shows discrepancies between the disciplinary treatment of Black and white students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/5907264/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/5907264/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/5907264&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systematic discrimination has historically plagued the U.S., and Evanston is not to spare. On top of housing, policing and education are two issues among the many others that culminate to form the lived experience for Black Americans everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About the Program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Reparations Restorative Housing Program won in an 8-1 vote by council members. The program’s overarching goal is to address the wealth and opportunity gaps experienced by Black residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Restorative Housing Program is the first initiative developed by the Reparations Subcommittee focused on preserving, stabilizing, and increasing homeownership, which builds intergenerational wealth among Black/African-American residents,” said members of the reparations subcommittee in their March 22 &lt;a href=&quot;https://cityofevanston.civicweb.net/document/50624/Adoption%20of%20Resolution%2037-R-27,%20Authorizing%20the.pdf?handle=E11C7B73E1B6470DA42362AB80A50C46&quot;&gt;memorandum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city has pledged to distribute the first $10 million generated by a 3 percent sales tax on recreational marijuana to qualifying residents. In the current stage of the program, $400,000 will be distributed to sixteen households to be used toward down payments and home repairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To qualify for the program, Black community members of African descent must prove that they were residents or related to residents of the city between 1919 and 1969, the timeframe in which Evanston actively enacted discriminatory housing policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Williams, opposition to the program began at town hall meetings where residents had conflicting ideas of what reparations should look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It became clear I think that those divisions were really deepening,” Williams said. “There was the sense that the group that doesn’t believe in direct payments was being listened to more than those that do believe in direct payments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singular dissenting vote came from Cicely Fleming, the ninth ward alderwoman and one of three Black council members. Fleming said she is “100% in support of reparations” in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cicelylfleming.com/blog/reparations&quot;&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; she gave to the rest of the council following the March 22 vote. However, these are not reparations — to Fleming, they are “a housing plan dressed up as reparations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We must understand the definition of true reparations and its main goal: to do that, the People dictate its terms to Power, not the other way around,” Fleming said in her statement. “Rather, this resolution is dictating to Black residents what they need and how they will receive what they need.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams echoed this sentiment. She added that the two biggest actors responsible for harming Evanston’s Black community, the banking and real estate industries, are the ones who will be rewarded with the $25,000 eligible recipients will receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It would be one thing not to charge any of these people fees or closing costs to acknowledge that they were complicit in this; that would be different,” Williams said. “But to just say we’re giving you money that you then have to spend on the two organizations that are responsible for impoverishing you in the first place makes absolutely no sense.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aldermen concluded that the strongest case for reparations lay in the realm of housing after the council was presented with evidence demonstrating disproportionate harm to Black residents from city zoning ordinances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Bader, Associate Professor of Sociology and Policy at American University, specializes in studying patterns of racial change in cities and neighborhoods. According to Bader, there is benefit to focusing on housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s an intergenerational transmission that if we invest in neighborhoods and invest in housing and improving neighborhood school conditions, we can eventually have benefits not only for the current generation to enjoy them but also for their kids,” Bader said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dino Robinson, Executive Director Shorefront Legacy Center, and Jenny Thompson, Director of Education at the Evanston History Center, presented their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cityofevanston.org/home/showpublisheddocument?id=59759&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, “Evanston Policies and Practices Directly Affecting the African American Community, 1900 - 1960 (and Present)” in August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since its platting, the city of Evanston both supported and created systems to segregate, limit, deny, and control Black citizens,” said Robinson and Thompson in their report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report outlined the combined efforts of Evanston’s banks, builders, realtors and government that limited Black mobility and livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Into the 1940s, the Home Owners’ Loan Corporation prepared a map evaluating the risk of making mortgage loans in different Evanston neighborhoods. A triangular area north of Church Street and bordered by the North Shore Channel was home to the city’s largest Black population. The same area was given a grade of “D” and shaded red – indicating ‘”undesirable population or an infiltration of it,”’ according to HOLC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same segregated boundaries present in the 1940s appear today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report also made clear that issues of housing were not the only things hurting Black residents, though they were most clearly compounded by the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming decade, the remaining millions of dollars will be distributed to Evanston’s Black residents through reparations to restore the damage done by housing practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, Black residents will likely continue to face persistent discrimination through systems such as housing, policing and education that have sustained this harmful, racist pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents like Williams have taken the initiative into their own hands. Williams’ synagogue, Tzedek Chicago, is working to implement its own reparations program for other congregants to pay into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The synagogue is working on how to make an actual commitment and not seeing it as a charitable donation but actually using it as a tax which I think is important,” Williams said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Evanston was the first city to issue reparations to its residents, it might not be the last. For some, this is a point of pride, and for others, it’s troubling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This isn’t change that can be a beacon for the nation,” Fleming said in her statement. “It is a dim, weak light. And it will be a travesty for Black communities around the U.S. if it becomes our model going forward.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bader believes that this initiative is a first step toward equality, but there needs to be something more expansive to make amends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The scale of the problem is just much bigger than Evanston,” Bader said. “It really needs to be handled at a federal level.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bader continued, “It’s not just a drop in the bucket; it’s a drop in the ocean.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:50:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/evanston-reparations/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/evanston-reparations/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How COVID-19 Has Impacted Student Enrollment Numbers</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-H2ApF&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/H2ApF/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the COVID-19 pandemic hit the United States in early 2020, universities across the nation saw enrollment rate changes across the board after announcing classes would be held online for the Fall 2020 academic semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What happened with COVID is, what we soon realized was that melt was going to be a lot higher,” Jonathan Akman, Associate Director and Business Analyst at American University, said. “And it was going to be higher for a few reason - meaning more of our enrollment deposits were going to go away.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Akman gave insight into the reality that students, who initially were enrolling to American University, were getting pulled off of the waitlist of other universities (that ranked higher than American University by these students’ preferences of colleges to attend] due to the low enrollment rates there. Due to this, more students were not enrolling at American University in Fall of 2020 than the previous Fall semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though American University saw a little difficulty with enrollment rates of students - and creating a new enrollment system around it - the District of Columbia as a whole saw an increase of enrollment numbers during the 2020 Fall academic semester for all colleges residing in the district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fall of 2019, the District of Columbia saw 70,717 students confirm their enrollment to a District of Columbia college/university. In Fall of 2020, that number went up by 3% (to 72,763 enrollments) for the same category of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-time-or-part-time-the-story-of-two-students&quot;&gt;Full-Time or Part-Time (The Story of Two Students)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-VR4uc&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/VR4uc/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-RY57o&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/RY57o/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think I was mostly disappointed, because I really like the benefits of being inside of a classroom,” Ashley Lopez, a second semester Junior at American University who is in the School of Communications, said. “And having a set schedule around going to classes and being on campus, and structuring my meals around that; instead of being at home and then just logging [onto classes] without any real structure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopez was looking forwards to enjoying their Fall semester in 2020 as a full-time student. Though they had second thoughts of deciding whether they should continue to be a full-time student or become a part-time one during the summer of 2020 (when it was announced classes would be fully online), Lopez decided to continue as a full-time student to complete their academic plan on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I just wanted to finish my degree on time,” Lopez said. “I did not want to finish any later than I had intended, so I was willing to go online [full-time]; even if it meant being more stressed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopez is part of the School of Communications, and in the Fall of 2020 (for full-time enrollment), the School of Communications was the fifth out of six majors to have the most full-time students in its school. They had 859 students enrolled in the school during Fall 2020, and that made up to 12% of the overall data collected for all majors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopez thought about being a part-time student during the Fall 2020 semester, but eventually dismissed the idea due to it not benefiting their academic plan of graduating on-time. The way their classes were set up, and the structure of credits, Lopez thought it would be overall easier to be a full-time student and go with their degree as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am taking 9 credits [for the Fall 2020 semester],” Madi Bendeck, an American University junior student, said. “And I am majoring in economics with a minor in political science.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bendeck attended American University online during the Fall 2020 semester as a part-time student. Bendeck joins 7,098 other students who attended their Fall 2020 semester part-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Affordability [was a big reason for going part-time],” Bendeck said. “The fact that I can graduate sorta on-time while being a part-time [student is nice]. So I saved over $10,000 per semester by, not only staying home, but also being a part-time student.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Lopez and Bendeck hope to return to American University in person as full-time students next Fall (Fall 2021) to complete their senior years with in-person class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;international-students&quot;&gt;International Students&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-cHcjG&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/cHcjG/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-zpKxT&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/zpKxT/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At American University, at least in the freshman class, is typically six-to-seven percent international [students],” Akman said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though for most countries, the rate of international students who enrolled at American University went down, but students who were from China actually went up in enrollment numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both Fall 2019 and Fall 2020, enrollment numbers for international students from China have been the number one spot of most enrolled from a singular country. In 2019, 421 students who were international and enrolled at American University were from China. That number went up by 133% (an additional 143 students) enrolled at American University from China in the Fall 2020 semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should also be pointed out that 27 students enrolled at American University, from Yemen, for their Bachelor’s degree, but for the Fall 2020 semester, no student from Yemen continued that enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the country of Panama, the country became the second international place where most students were enrolling to American University over seas. Though their number of enrolled students went from 22 to 21 students, they moved up from the fourth spot to the second spot right behind China of most students enrolled from an exact country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking into the future, Akman describes the lessons that were learned as a university in the case that another global pandemic happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Being flexible, as an office and as a university more broadly, we have accepted being confronted with uncertainty,” Akman said. “Giving that uncertainty, we had to be more creative. We have had to think about trade-offs. Benefiting at one area at the expense of another.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full enrollment numbers for Fall 2021 will be coming out in the near future according to the American University Office of Enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:50:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/covid-19-college-enrollment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/covid-19-college-enrollment/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The relationship between mass-shootings and suicides</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As high-profile mass shootings have increased in frequency over the past twenty-five years, a pattern has emerged in those who carry out these attacks. Most often the attacker is revealed to usually be middle-class, White, and male. Whether it be Stephen Paddock, Adam Lanza, or James Holmes they all share these characteristics. Similarly, in America, suicides are disproportionately carried out by members of the exact same gender, race, and economic backgrounds. Using data compiled by The Violence Project on Mass Shootings as well as the CDC’s suicide data revealed that half of all mass shooters were White males and that suicides make up for a third of White male deaths. The parallels in statistical groups are not just in gender and race, shootings and suicides are both correlated to be committed in middle-class areas by middle-class perpetrators. This article seeks to show overlapping similarities between incidents, not to make generalized statements about racial groups nor is it to prove a direct connection between identity characteristics and these acts.
Suicide data from the CDC shows an overwhelming majority of suicide victims are male as well as White. These characteristics are similar to those of mass shooters as data from The Violence Project revealed. According to the data provided, ninety-eight percent of mass shooters were male, and over half were White. These statistics alone do not reveal direct causation, just a correlation between White males and these acts. This still leaves a question to be answered, why? White males are statistically the most economically and socially privileged in this country, yet they are one of the most likely to commit acts of self-destruction or mass killing. Part of it certainly has to do with population, Whites make up the largest racial population in the country so there is a certain sense to their statistical dominance. Still, amongst men, Whites make up the greatest percentage of suicides per 100,000 behind Native Americans, Blacks and Asians follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/6030425/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/6030425/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/6030425&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/6030513/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/6030513/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/6030513&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/6031420/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/6031420/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/6031420&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;correlations-between-suicide-and-mass-shootings&quot;&gt;Correlations Between Suicide and Mass Shootings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suicide and mass shootings have more than these basic race and gender statistical similarities. Mass Shooters also have a direct connection with suicide as many shooters either kill themselves during the act or had previously been suicidal. The Violence Project revealed that nearly three-quarters of mass shooters fell into either of these two categories. Thirty percent were previously suicidal, and forty percent intended to die during the act. Again, half of these male mass shooters were White showing another correlation between the two acts and racial groups. Another correlation between suicide and mass shootings is the weapon of choice, firearms. Firearms are used in all mass shootings, however, their prevalence as a suicide method is worth mentioning. CDC data shows that White males were seven times more likely than females of any race to commit suicide by firearm. Comparing all suicides to White male suicides within the same age range, also showed that White men killed themselves with firearms double the amount of the national average.
Arielle Geismar is a youth gun violence activist whose work has intersected both mass shootings, and suicide. She has worked as a National Organizing Fellow for Team Enough of the Brady Campaign United Against Gun Violence. I asked her why the profile of mass shooters was so skewed towards White males. “The profile of the mass shooter typically is a White male. Often, he is ostracized in some form either socially or neglected by his parents. This is strange however because statistically White males are some of the most catered to especially within a school environment.” Speaking on why White men commit suicide at a disproportionate rate she had this to say. “I can’t speak to the exact reason it’s disproportionate, but I do know that most Veteran and White rural male suicides are gun suicides. This may contribute to why White males commit suicide more than other groups.” Finally, I asked her why in her opinion both issues were overly prevalent for White men. “I think it has to do with White male, and maybe just male temperament in this country. Men are not taught ways to reach out for emotional help, but what they are given is ample and easy access to guns. It’s terrible, but it makes some sense as to why men unequally end up turning weapons against themselves or others.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Mass Shooting Location by State&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-NPn5u&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/NPn5u/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border: none;&quot; width=&quot;832&quot; height=&quot;596&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/6032381/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/6032381/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/6032381&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two types of incidents, mass-shootings, and suicides diverge categorically in terms of class. Mass shooters and the areas they occur typically follow a trend of being middle to upper class and occurring in suburban or urban areas. The Violence Project’s data showed that nearly sixty percent of shooters grew up either middle or upper class and nearly ninety percent of shootings occurred in suburban or urban areas. Speaking with Mary Dillon an intern at The Violence Project she explained that “There definitely is a correlation between mass-shootings and suburban and urban areas. My understanding is that rural areas simply having lower populations concentrations lowers the chance of mass shootings but not gun violence in general.” This shows a correlating trend between mass shootings, relative economic prosperity, and relatively dense living communities. Additionally, eighty percent of White shooters grew up either middle or upper class in comparison with only one-quarter of black shooters. Again, this percentage alone is not enough to make any definitive connection, however, it does beg a question why are so many White shooters from relatively prosperous economic backgrounds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most surprising facts revealed by the map was poorer rural states such as West Virginia, New Mexico, and Alabama, which all have high rates of gun ownership, had little to no recorded mass shootings. In contrast, the Denver county area which has a median household income of $75,000 has suffered at least five attacks alone according to The Violence Project. This data contrasts with the suicide data provided by the CDC which shows suicide rates being higher in poor White rural states like West Virginia, Alaska, and Montana. While both suicide and mass shootings are unequally committed by White males, the reason their correlation diverges on socio-economic status may have to do with the intent and circumstances of these actions. This article is not intended to show that suicide and mass shootings are interconnected as acts, rather it is to show the statistical anomalies present within both groups that correlate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-common-class&quot;&gt;A Common Class&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/6037352/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/6037352/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/6037352&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This map compares every mass shooting in Colorado with the median household income of each zip code. Every shooting location within Colorado had a higher than average median income when in comparison to the rest of the country. Only two Colorado shootings took place in an area with a median income lower than the national median of $65,000. Both attacks happened in Aurora, with median incomes coming close to $60,000. Additionally, neither attacker was from the area according to the data collected by The Violence Project. Looking further, the surrounding zip codes around Aurora have far higher median incomes than the national average. The most recent shooting in Boulder Colorado which took the lives of ten people, occurred in a zip code with a median income of $90,000 a year, close to one and a half times the national average. Additionally, the locations of the Columbine Shooting, Arvada, and Boulder all border zip codes with a median income of over $100,000. Within the context of Colorado, this shows not only a correlation between mass shootings and suburban areas but also with higher levels of wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this map shows basic statistics of the area, Google Street View can give us a more accurate picture of the areas these types of attacks take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!4v1620055240399!6m8!1m7!1sfBzrUh2TAJ3Mgsau_XUqJQ!2m2!1d39.6016682351057!2d-105.0777854871066!3f350.12086303145037!4f1.612307789875743!5f1.1924812503605782&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; style=&quot;border:0;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Google Street View shows a cul-de-sac less than a five-minute walk away from Columbine High School in Littleton Colorado. The street view of the neighborhoods around Columbine as well as a birds-eye view in Google Maps reveals that the area surrounding the high school is home to a manicured golf course, aquarium, mall, and amusement park. According to census data, the median income of Columbine’s zip code is $83,000, close to one and a half times more than the national average of $65,000. Just a thirty-minute drive away, the Aurora Theatre tells a similar socio-economic story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!4v1620056965770!6m8!1m7!1sC3aER3f41yaZGazLfUj8iw!2m2!1d39.701631872353!2d-104.8175856622377!3f31.64030276901266!4f1.2221024991407603!5f0.7820865974627469&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; style=&quot;border:0;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Google Street View of a cul-de-sac next to the Aurora Theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The median income for the Aurora Theatre zip code is $56,000 dollars. This is lower than Colorado and the national median, however, this shooting differs from Columbine as the shooter was not raised in the area. The Violence Project records the shooter, James Holmes, as coming from a middle-class background.According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-18937513&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; he was Ph.D. student in neuroscience at the University of Colorado, an institution with a yearly tuition cost of $35,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These specific shootings speak to the statistical anomaly seen in Colorado, as well as the rest of the US. The tendency for shooters to be middle or upper class and attack middle-class areas. The fact that most of the Colorado shooters have been White, sparing the most recent shooting in Boulder, is less significant in a nearly seventy percent White state. However, the rates of shootings in Colorado stand out more when comparing them to poorer more diverse states with similar populations. Colorado and Alabama have similar population demographics of having about five million people, as well as both, having a nearly seventy percent White population. Alabama and Colorado also share similar geographic proportions of rural, urban, and suburban populations. Where they differ is in income and amount of mass shootings. As stated previously Colorado has endured seven mass shootings in the past twenty-five years, in that same time, Alabama has had one. Despite having a higher level of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/215655/number-of-registered-weapons-in-the-us-by-state/&quot;&gt;gun ownership&lt;/a&gt;, Alabama has seen far fewer mass shootings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These correlations reveal a trend in the US between White, middle-class, males and these two events. While suicide and mass shootings themselves as acts are not directly correlated, they share statistical similarities in gender and race. The further finding of mass shootings being correlated to higher levels of wealth creates more questions than it answers. The rates of suicide being higher in lower class, rural areas make relative sense, what does not is the connection between relative prosperity and mass shootings. As our nation comes out of the Coronavirus pandemic, the re-opening of America has already come with an increase in gun violence and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2021/03/23/2020-shootings/&quot;&gt;mass-shootings&lt;/a&gt;. As it continues, additional measures will need to be put in place, not only to curve gun violence at large, a monumental task but also to address where and why they are happening. Mental health and other pre-determining factors are issues I have not even discussed in this piece, and most certainly should be addressed to reduce violent acts such as mass shootings and suicide. Still, curbing gun accessibility and increasing mental health services will not answer the question of why these high-profile shootings occur in middle-class America.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:49:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/mass-shootings-suicides/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/mass-shootings-suicides/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>COVID Deaths in People Under the Age of 25 highlight Fatal Year</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The ongoing COVID-19 pandemic has affected more age groups more severely than others. To date there have been 557,486 deaths resulting from the coronavirus. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid_weekly/index.htm#ExcessDeaths&quot;&gt;Data from the CDC&lt;/a&gt; shows that the bulk of deaths were people over the age of 50. It is well established that COVID-19 has a greater effect on the elderly than it does on the young. However, this is not to say that younger people are immune from the virus and death. 2020 saw an 8.7% increase in deaths from 2019 in people under the age of 25. 2020 also saw a 3.5% rise in deaths of people under the age of 25 when compared to the yearly average between 2016-2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/6061276&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the numbers for 2020 are not significantly greater than the numbers in any other year measured. 2020 unlike the other years shown has a significant public health event that drives its numbers up. COVID-19 has proven to not be overly deadly to this age demographic. Collectively in 2020 and 2021 there have been 8,485 COVID Deaths for people under the age of 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as it concerns excess death reporting there was an increase in deaths since the onset of the pandemic. Combined death data from the years 2020 and 2021 subtracted from COVID deaths in this age demographic left 11,483 deaths over the average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemediacentre.org/expert-reaction-to-study-looking-at-excess-deaths-during-the-covid-19-first-wave-in-21-countries/&quot;&gt;In an interview with Nature Medicine&lt;/a&gt;, Professor Kevin McConway suggests that looking at excess deaths is the best way to understand COVID’s effect on mortality. “Just looking at the numbers of deaths attributed to Covid-19 is problematic. What counts as a Covid-19 death is defined differently in different countries.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inconsistencies in the way that COVID deaths are reported have been well documented.  Anesthesiologist from Maryland, Dr. Nikolus Visnich describes a chaotic scene on the frontlines of the pandemic, “We were unprepared, undermanned, lacking in PPE, and no one knew what the policies were.” “Everchanging policies and procedures made it harder to compartimentalize what was occurring,”” Dr. Visnich explained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Dr. Visnich did not describe was a significant uptick in the hospitalizations of people under the age of 25. Dr. Visnich explained that elective procedures had to be halted and that the hospital was noticeably emptied of anything that wasn’t related to COVID. Dr. Visnich did experience a rush of appendectomies in teenagers at one point during the summer. Dr. Visnich suggested that less people were coming to hospitals. He thought this was two-pronged, there was a significant public health crisis and there wasn’t time to focus on other things, but he also suggested that people fear hospitals in the current climate. “If people can’t feel safe in a space designed to help them, then they won’t seek help.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not relying on public services in times of need no doubt shifted the public’s attitude towards the medical system. Attitudinal shifts result in behavioral changes. Changes that very likely caused an increase in death. To understand what an increase in death means is to understand what is happening in the big picture of society. Discrepancies in the way COVID deaths are reported from place to place coupled different societal actions in response to a pandemic are what must be sorted to understand the implications of excess death in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McConway in the same interview suggests that the pandemic’s wide-reaching effect can drive up deaths in certain directions while driving them down in others. To McConway it is a matter of defining what a COVID death constitutes. “That entirely avoids the issue of what counts as a COVID death, and it also picks up extra deaths that occur because of changes to health services that restrict access to cancer treatments, for example, as well as possible reductions in deaths, maybe because there’s less traffic and fewer road accidents during lockdowns.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policies differ from hospital to hospital and state by state. The states with the highest populations such as California, Florida, New York, and Texas reported the most COVID deaths in people under the age of 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-map&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/5916390&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we see is that most states didn’t have a death in this age demographic, while the major population centers such as Texas, California, Florida, and New York all experienced death tolls in the hundreds. The majority of states did not have a COVID death in the under 25 age demographic, but the major increases in California, Florida, New York, and Texas have accounted for a rise nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-map&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/5916504&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data that excludes COVID deaths shows a similar trend to the COVID death data. The major population centers Texas, California, Florida, and New York lead the way in excess deaths in people under the age of 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spikes in excess deaths have accompanied spikes in COVID deaths in this age demographic. The size and population of states that demonstrate this trend should be noted. Even in normal years, California, Florida, New York, and Texas are among states with the highest deaths in those under the age of 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be years before we fully understand where the 11,000 excess deaths have come from since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. The effects of the pandemic have had major societal ramifications. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Z9b5mIwztAwmEHJW7Q5DHMjS14-Rs7XIXOt33Al_rDw/edit#gid=1757262194&quot;&gt;Homicides were up 35.2% from 2019 in 2020&lt;/a&gt;. Non-COVID hospitalizations were low. True lasting impacts are yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 was a chaotic year, lockdowns, societal unrest, and economic struggles were present. To what extent these factors had on the youth of the country is yet to be determined. But what the numbers show is an above average year in the death of young people resulting from the effects of an ongoing pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fully understand the ramifications of COVID-19, death reporting ought to be better categorized and defined. The lack of a consistent definition of what a COVID death is, no doubt has muddled the picture on where the uptick of death has come from. But it is clear where COVID goes death follows.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:49:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/covid-deaths-young-people/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/covid-deaths-young-people/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Restrictiveness of State Gun Laws is Associated with School Shootings</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A generation of students has been raised to fear school shootings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;K-12 Shootings Since Columbine&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-kltZh&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/kltZh/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;449&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been over 1,000 incidents of gun violence in the United States reported in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chds.us/ssdb/data-map/&quot;&gt;K-12 School Shooting Database&lt;/a&gt; since the Columbine High School massacre on April 20, 1999. With that, comes over twenty-six hundred victims either injured or killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of children who witness the violence and/or experience PTSD and other forms of anxiety disorders due to gun violence at school is more than a staggering &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2018/local/school-shootings-database/?utm_term=.31abe27c1082&quot;&gt;248,000&lt;/a&gt;. Students now worry more about a shooting happening at their school than &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.childrensdefense.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/YouGov-SafeSchools-Final-Sep-18-2018.pdf&quot;&gt;peer pressure&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the gun violence children experience in the United States, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/19/us/politics/nra-gun-control.html&quot;&gt;gun lobbyist&lt;/a&gt; groups continue to block progress in Washington. The gun lobby has long perpetuated an extremist view of the Second Amendment, with no wiggle room for common sense gun safety protections. With the right laws, school shootings can be prevented. States with stronger gun laws have less gun violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the Stoneman Douglas High School shooting in 2018, which resulted in the deaths of 17 students, Wayne LaPieree, the CEO of the NRA called for arming teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every day, young children are being dropped off at schools that are virtually wide-open, soft targets for anyone bent on mass murder,” said LaPieree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giffords.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/The-Truth-About-School-Shootings-Report.pdf&quot;&gt;Studies&lt;/a&gt; have shown that the risks associated with gun access vastly outweigh the likelihood of self-defense use. “Whether or not I’m pro-gun, I don’t wan’t a gun in the classroom, it puts my students in unnecessary danger.” said Toni Jones, a kindergarten teacher for DCPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students across the nation already go through anxiety-inducing active-shooter drills, a gun is an added stress. “When we go into lockdown, the kids are scared because someone is tugging at the door, I have to reassure the kids they are safe, even if I can’t guarantee it,” said Jones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threats of an active-shooter negatively impact students’ learning and overall school experience. In addition to the emotional toll of regular drills and frequent shootings across the country, the family partnerships are also harmed. Jones notes, “New security and growing fears of threats against the school doesn’t allow for a lot of family relationships, we can’t have volunteers in the class like we used to.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While guns in the classroom is not the answer, Jones acknowledges there is a fine line between school safety and over policing, which tends to disproportionately punish students-of-color. “The current system needs to be redesigned and reformed, so we can feel safe at school, without having to worry about which students are getting unfairly punished.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008 ruling in the &lt;em&gt;District of Columbia v. Heller&lt;/em&gt; marked the first Supreme Court ruling on the Second Amendment in nearly 70 years. The court ruled in favor of Dick Heller who sued D.C. over its ban at handguns in the home. In the decision, Justice Scalia affirmed the individual’s right to keep handguns at one’s home for self-defense, while still stressing the limited nature of the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Like most rights, the right secured by the Second Amendment is not unlimited. [It is] not a right to keep and carry any weapon whatsoever in any manner whatsoever and for whatever purpose.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Gun Laws by State&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-i9wiq&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/i9wiq/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;483&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to gun laws, states vary on everything from background check procedures to mental health reporting. The vast difference of gun laws and ownership by states attributes to gun violence. For instance, California, Massachusetts, and Connecticut have the most laws on the books all around approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statefirearmlaws.org&quot;&gt;one-hundred&lt;/a&gt;, while Iowa and Idaho are tied for dead last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firearms left unsecured in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://giffords.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/The-Truth-About-School-Shootings-Report.pdf&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1619583672120000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw32IFV5_6lv0MnzXKytfzwa&quot;&gt;home&lt;/a&gt; are a major source of guns used in school shootings. With that being said, it is essential to have an accurate record of gun sales. An accurate record can help keep guns out of undesirable hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Child access prevention (CAP) laws encourage safe storage of firearms by holding adults accountable when children gain access to their guns. Evidence shows these laws work to prevent unauthorized firearm access. A 1997 &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/418289&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; found that CAP laws were associated with a 23% decrease in accidental shooting death among children younger than 15-years-old. Fourteen states have implemented CAP laws, but specifics vary. The majority of states with CAP laws require the child to use the firearm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-slope&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/5987013&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four states, California, Massachusetts, Minnesota, and Maryland have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://giffords.org/lawcenter/gun-laws/policy-areas/child-consumer-safety/child-access-prevention/&quot;&gt;strictest&lt;/a&gt; CAP laws that impose criminal liability when a minor is merely likely to gain access to a gun that is negligently stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;73-percent of children under 10 living in homes with guns reported knowing the location of their parents’ firearms, and 36-percent admitted they had &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapediatrics/fullarticle/204929&quot;&gt;handled&lt;/a&gt; the weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With over 700 thousand registered guns, Texas has the most firearms of any state. Additionally, Texas has the most school shootings in the county, per 100 thousand people. Followed by Louisiana, Delaware, and Alabama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The states with the lowest rates of gun violence in K-12 schools, since Columbine, are Massachusetts, New York, North Dakota and Hawaii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on existing gun laws, legal gun ownership, and previous school shootings, Idaho, Missouri, Iowa, Texas, and Georgia have the least amount of measures in place to prevent gun violence, when taking into account the amount of registered guns in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restrictiveness of state gun laws is associated with the rate of school shootings in the United States. This has a major impact on K-12 students. Children who experience school shootings can suffer severe anxiety and debilitating trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jill Bohnenkamp, an assistant professor and faculty at the Center for School Mental Health at the University of Maryland, spoke on the effect of living in the current climate of gun violence. Dr. Bohnenkamp has experience in school mental health research, policy and clinical practice at the local, state, and national levels. Her research focuses on school safety outcomes of school mental health service provisions and mental health training for educators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pervasive gun violence contributes to feelings of unsafety in school. Teachers are integral to addressing children’s mental health needs in schools, yet they report limited training in mental health and behavior management in the classroom”, said Dr. Bohnenkamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SAS estimates that American citizens own &lt;a href=&quot;https://wamu.org/story/20/09/18/how-many-people-in-the-u-s-own-guns/&quot;&gt;393 million guns&lt;/a&gt;, making the U.S. ranked number one in firearms per capita. A majority of gun owners cite &lt;em&gt;protection&lt;/em&gt; as their primary reason for owning a gun. A 2015 Harvard &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0091743515001188&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; found that people defended themselves with a gun in less than 1 percent of 14 thousand crimes from 2007-11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.acpjournals.org/doi/10.7326/M13-1301&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1619584295209000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0J4L30HWAGNy3ndJ_SeSEO&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has shown that guns in the home are far more likely to be used for suicide or homicide, rather than for self-defense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of effective policy solutions can better protect children from violence. &lt;a href=&quot;https://giffords.org/issues/kids-and-guns/&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt; indicates, closing background check loopholes, investing in community-based violence intervention programs, and child access prevention laws can have positive impacts on the current rate of gun violence affecting children in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:48:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/school-shootings-restrictive-gun-laws/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/school-shootings-restrictive-gun-laws/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Homeless Vermonters still struggle to find affordable housing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“I think I pay close to 50% of my income for my housing. As a single parent, even for me, that’s hard. 50% of my income goes right to my rent, and that doesn’t include anything. Is that affordable?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martina Newell has never been homeless before, but she knows that if she were to suddenly lose her job, housing insecurity might not follow far behind. She is also the direct services manager at Samaritan House, a nonprofit dedicated to fighting homelessness and supporting homeless people in the town of St. Albans and the surrounding county – in other words, she is not much different from the people she tries to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her direct work with her clients and her personal experience have shown her that contrary to the popular image of homelessness, which is often defined by extreme poverty and a housed versus not housed dichotomy, anyone can be in danger of losing their home. “There’s increasingly an amount of people that are living paycheck to paycheck, making really good wages, but have a traumatic life event,” she says, which leaves them without a place to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to other states in the US’s New England region, Vermont has the second highest amount of homeless people per capita, second only to the much more urban Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Homeless Population per 500,000 People in New England&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-qAx21&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/qAx21/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;773&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the COVID-19 pandemic, the vacancy rate for affordable housing in Vermont ranged from 0.5% to 2%. When the pandemic started spreading into the state, many agencies’ congregate shelters had to close. To compensate for this, the Vermont General Assistance program, which normally has stricter regulations on eligibility for homeless status based on those used by the US Department of Housing and Urban Development – petitioners cannot have caused their own homelessness or be doubled up with other households, for example – loosened its requirements and started relocating homeless individuals and families to hotels. The main problem for the state is moving these people out of hotels when there are next to no affordable houses for them to move into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Vermont is a very expensive place to live in,” Newell says. In fact, Vermont has a higher overall cost of living than many other US states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Cost of Living Index by State in 2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-X9nxl&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/X9nxl/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;487&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many homeless people in Vermont find themselves traveling to its southeasternmost county, near the town of Brattleboro. Libby Bennett, who works with the Brattleboro-based homelessness support nonprofit Groundworks Collaborative, says, “People who are homeless in other parts of the state are, for lack of a better word, being sent here by the state.” While their case managers in other parts of the state are communicating with them through phone or video calls, Groundworks does its best to assist them in the Brattleboro area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model Groundworks and other Vermont nonprofits use is one they call the “three-legged stool” of subsidies, support, and brick-and-mortar housing. Governor Phil Scott has recently allocated $249 million to affordable housing and homelessness prevention in the state, and Groundworks has doubled the size of its case management team from 5 to 10 people since the COVID-19 pandemic started. Bennett believes that physical housing units are the one leg missing from the state’s efforts. “In Vermont, the resources for the three legs never roll out together,” she says. Vermont’s low vacancy rates for affordable housing have changed little over the past year, and the coronavirus has only placed further pressure and given further visibility to an already strained system. Bennett says, “It was always an extreme situation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vermont’s heavily rural demographics differentiate the state’s homelessness problem from those in more urban areas, and nowhere is this clearer than in its Northeast Kingdom region, comprised of Essex, Orleans, and Caledonia Counties. The latter two are the counties with the highest number of total COVID-19 cases since the start of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;COVID-19 Infections in Vermont by County&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-CERFN&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/CERFN/4/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;792&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before COVID-19, it was not uncommon for people to move in with other households, according to Jenna O’Farrell, executive director of Northeast Kingdom Community Action. “Especially in the Northeast Kingdom, I think people are pretty resourceful and would stay with relatives, and maybe in unsafe situations,” she says, “but they maybe didn’t meet the HUD standards for homelessness because they were doubled up.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O’Farrell also believes that the state has struggled to accurately assess its own housing needs in its yearly point-in-time homelessness count. Vermont makes its count in January, when many people are going out of their way to find places to live in the winter. “If you did the point-in-time count in July, when you literally do have homeless folks out on the street in downtown areas, your count would be much different. But doing the homelessness count on a 10-below night in January is not going to get us accurate data,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O’Farrell describes individual communities’ populations of homeless people as “right-sized to the demographics,” regardless of how rural or urban they are, citing the more urban Chittenden County with its higher homeless population as an example. She adds, “Local communities come up with local solutions to meet that number.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newell says that the root of homelessness can often be persistent; Vermonters raised in state-sponsored housing as children may struggle to find a livable wage as adults and find themselves in the same situation as before. In her opinion, generational problems require lasting, generational solutions, ones that go beyond the expenditure of state money on the right causes and focus on strong, mutually supportive communities. “Yeah, you can build all these affordable houses, but you need people in these positions to make sure that they’re continuing on,” she says. “It’s not like you can say, ‘We’ll put them in here, and then they’re good.’”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:48:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/homeless-vermont/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/homeless-vermont/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DC homeless residents receive aid, vaccination wealth gap expands</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With COVID-19 vaccinations becoming more widespread across DC, homeless residents are receiving the help they need, with over 50% of documented homeless people vaccinated. While this is good news for DC’s most vulnerable residents, this does not reflect the overall trend in vaccinations - and more importantly, who is receiving them the most. Research finds that the wealthiest wards in DC have received the most vaccines, while DC’s poorest wards, the areas that have seen the most COVID deaths in DC, have received the fewest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;bar chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-ORi6a&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/ORi6a/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DC’s wards have roughly equal population across the city, with an average population of about 74,000 people. This makes it easy to spot that, while Wards 1, 3 and 6 have more than 20% of their populations partially or fully vaccinated, Wards 7 and 8 have less than half that. The contrast becomes clear when putting these Wards side by side; Ward 6, an area that has an average income of $108,000, has vaccinated 17,174 of its current residents as of April. Ward 8, with an average income of $34,000, have vaccinated less than 8,000 - less than half that of Ward 6. While Ward 8 saw a similar number of COVID cases as Ward 6, Ward 8 had nearly twice the number of COVID deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;bar chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-NgRL8&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/NgRL8/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many would assume that DC’s vocal initiative to aid the homeless during this time is positive, and overall, it seems like the Department of Health and Human Services has made great strides in accommodating the homeless community. For example, on March 8, Dr. Laquandra Nesbitt, director of the Department of Health, said that “close to 50%” of documented homeless people had received their first dose of the vaccine. Laura Green Zeilinger, director of the Department of Human Services, said that close to 30% of DC’s ‘undocumented’ homeless people, that is homeless people that do not stay in shelters, received the first dose of the vaccine. In their first week of vaccination rollouts for homeless shelters, Unity Health Care, one of the major nonprofits leading the rollouts, reported that 300-400 homeless residents received their first dose of the vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abdul Ayuba, was among one of those who received their first shot of the vaccine. Ayuba is a homeless resident of DC who has lived in the city for over a decade. Ayuba received his first vaccine from a local CVS in Tenleytown, and is currently awaiting his second dose in a week. “I was registered, and then one day, a CVS worker was saying they had extra shots they needed to give away. I walked in and got it, no problem.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is combined with the fact that DC’s homeless population as of last year was the lowest it has been in 20 years, and is on a slow, but steady decline. Family homelessness dropped 48% in the last five years alone. With all of this progress, many would assume Mayor Bowser and the DC Council is doing everything in their power to help. However, this overlooks several crucial components that may make DC’s helping hand seem less helpful than imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to evaluate the reasons behind the general disparity of vaccines by Ward. When DC first announced its rollout plan earlier this year, the locations for mass vaccinations were primarily in downtown DC, the wealthiest area of the city. Despite DC’s attempt to make pre-registering more successful, such as lowering eligibility age and focusing on Zip codes, these efforts backfired, opening up more people from wealthier areas for eligibility than those living in those areas in the first place. This created an influx of mostly rich, mostly white, DC residents traveling to low-income wards to receive the vaccine before its local residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yared Abay, a resident of Ward 5, expressed his issues with this disparity. Abay had been pre-registered for over a month when I spoke to him on April 16. Abay is an Uber driver who has lived near Fort Totten for much of his time in the US. Abay, eligible for the vaccine, when asked when he was anticipating getting his first shot, responded “Who knows?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve seen the lines at the Covid vaccine locations, most of them are not from the area.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, I received my first dose of the vaccine less than three days after registering as a Ward 2 resident, more than a month after Abay had registered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important when considering why homeless residents have been receiving more aid than many would have expected given the disparity in vaccine rollouts. Ward 6 in DC, making up the central downtown of the city, has the most homeless facilities compared to any other part of the city, with five homeless shelters and housing locations, as well as 24 other service locations for homeless residents. That’s almost double the amount in Wards 7 and 8. One of the first locations Unity Health Care visited was Central Union Mission in March, where they completed their initial 300-400 doses administered in their first week. This highlights a potential problem with DC’s self-praise in regards to homeless vaccinations: many of these homeless people were likely vaccinated out of convenience of location rather than hardcore outreach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot; &quot; aria-label=&quot;bar chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-OSh3c&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/OSh3c/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it makes sense when you consider the experiences of homeless shelters employees outside of Ward 6. Dia Zorilla, a representative of Casa Ruby, one of the only homeless shelters in Ward 5 with only 17 available beds, reported that while they do require a negative COVID test confirmation for residents to stay, they did not mention any coordination with Unity Healthcare. This isn’t the case across all small shelters in DC, like New York Avenue Men’s Shelter, where director Michael Ferrell stated that Unity Health Care visits every other week for two days out of the week, consistent with Unity Health Care’s goals stated in March. The inconsistency must be noted, however, as shelters now are under serious financial burden and anymore missteps during this time is lethal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While DC has made great strides to improve the conditions of unhoused residents during the pandemic, their negligence in addressing vaccine disparities must be acknowledged while our struggle with Covid-19 still wages.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:48:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/dc-homeless/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/dc-homeless/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How New York counties continue to approach and adapt to COVID-19</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;New York especially struggled in the early onset of the coronavirus outbreak. The entire population was hit hard by the pandemic, and the economy statewide declined as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of April 19, 2021, NY Department of Health reports that more than 49 million people total have been tested for COVID and nearly 2 million of these tests have been positive. Today alone, 116,483 people have been tested in NYS and nearly 3.5% of these tests are positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDC reports a total of 31,231,869 coronavirus cases in the United States and 561,356 deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently though, bustle has slowly returned to the Big Apple and its surrounding counties. Vaccine rollout statewide has sped up, and cases have started to decline, allowing New York to emerge as an underdog. Nationwide, 198 million total vaccines have been administered. New York state has seen 39.6% of its population with at least one vaccine dose, and 26.4% with completed vaccine series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed&quot; data-src=&quot;story/849657&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading this statewide comeback is Tompkins County, where the total population is 102,793 and there are 8.9 daily new cases per 100,000 people. There is an infection rate of 0.74, and county officials continue to maintain enforced safe guidelines to slow the spread of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximately 32% of these individuals are fully vaccinated. Tompkins County reports 56.7% of their population has at least one vaccine dose, but county officials are aiming for at least 75% of the community fully vaccinated by early summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wouldn’t be surprised if we hit that 70-75% mark in June,” says Dominick Recckio, Tompkins County Communications Director. “We’re gonna run up against people who are hesitant but really I expect that number to be just about where we end up.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/5871345&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The county is reliant on vaccines as their best defense against the virus, but masks are still worn to stay safe. A NYT survey indicated 83.3% of the Tompkins County population always wears masks, a common practice among most New York residents in any given county, while only 1.2% never wears masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve definitely seen people at the Walmart not wearing masks from time to time and no one says anything,” says Ian Landrigan, undergraduate senior at Ithaca College. “But everywhere else is very strict. It is expected that you wear a mask no matter where you are on campus and people definitely will give you looks if you aren’t wearing one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;NY Counties and Sum of Individuals Wearing Masks&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-lYSrh&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/lYSrh/4/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;608&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These community-wide efforts to promote safety have especially been important, as colleges plan for the upcoming fall semester. This past spring semester, both Cornell University and Ithaca College have hosted students on campus, but maintained a relatively remote approach to learning. Both universities will mandate vaccinations for students on-campus and plan to return to in-person learning for the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have been on campus both semesters this year. It has felt very safe and generally everyone follows COVID guidelines,” shares Hannah Davis, sophomore undergraduate student at Cornell University. “You have to reserve study spots, there are designated eating tables, and masks are worn everywhere on campus. Upon arrival, we have to quarantine until the people we are living with get a negative test result.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every student at the university is tested twice a week, while members of athletics and Greek life are tested three times a week. The university also has a dashboard available to the public, which informs of COVID data, including testing data, vaccination data, and the state of risk present on campus. Davis feels confident in the county and university’s evolving resources and methods to stay connected with community members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/5917583/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/5917583/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/5917583&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Tompkins County has continued efforts to limit the spread of the virus, other New York counties continue to struggle for a multitude of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chautauqua County has the highest infection rate of 1.14, and active cases continue to rapidly increase daily. This county, with a population of approximately 130,000 people, sees 27.1 daily new cases per 100k and has an 8.6% positive test rate. This county is at very high risk, with only 38.9% of its population vaccinated with a first dose and 55% of ICU capacity used as of today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richmond County also is at increasingly very high risk, with 52.7 daily new cases per 100k – a dangerous number considering the county’s population of nearly 480,000 people. The infection rate is 0.94, allowing for a slow spread of the virus, but the county’s positive test rate of 5.9% indicates sufficient testing. Still, only 39% of the population has received a first dose of the vaccine and only 27% is fully vaccinated. The county is at 75% ICU capacity used and although it can likely manage a new wave of the virus, there is still a very high risk at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allegany County meanwhile has the lowest vaccination rate, with only 29.5% of the population of 46,000 people having been vaccinated with their first dose. This area still is at high risk, with an infection rate of 0.93 and positive test rate of 6.8% indicating the county’s average vulnerability level in comparison to other U.S. counties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that President Biden has met his April 19 deadline for all adults in the U.S. to be eligible for COVID-19 vaccines, there is a greater chance for these New York counties to progress. The United States administers approximately 3.2 million vaccine doses daily, and approximately 84.3 million people have been completely vaccinated, according to the CDC. In the meantime, residents of New York surrounding counties should continue making efforts to contribute to their communities’ safety and wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:47:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/ny-covid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/ny-covid/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The coronavirus pet adoption boom: How new owners and shelters are responding to the increasing demand of pets</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Animal shelters has seen increased the demand in adoption rates for both cats and dogs, as the pandemic hit the United States which has kept more people at home. Local shelters and nationwide shelters along with rescue groups have seen double the number of people who have reached out inquiring about  adopting an animal between March of 2020 until the present. With an increase of 96% adoption rate for dogs, and 103% for cats, according to a report by Shelter Animals Count published on November of 2020. Shelters have been dealing with virtual adoptions that slow down the process of adoption, but this has kept future pet owners busy looking for other alternatives in local shelters or shelters outside their residence states. Katherine Barker who manages Pets Bring Joy,an animal rescue and charity organization serving the DC area, saving lives of older cats and dogs who are often not taken for adoption because they are not puppies or kittens anymore. “Cats are our only adoptable animals on Pets Bring Joy, anything from senior to kittens”, the interest in adopting cats has broken apart from the stereotype of adopting dogs, cats are now seen as viable company for both couples and families&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;National Adoption Rate&quot; aria-label=&quot;bar chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-Gs656&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Yh4UQ/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pet adoptions have always been an option for anyone who is willing to acquire a pet as company, with the many options possible, over the past year there has been a trend for preference of adopting cats as their first option, and dogs as their second option. According to Forbes and The Washington Post, this has all started between the Millenials and Generation Z, in this generation there has been the presence of pets during their childhoods most specifically dogs, years later when this generations have the means to be able to care for a pet they have chosen to adopt cats. “I like adopting cats because of their independence, in my case my cat is a special needs cat which requires more time consumed towards her, but I consider that cats are a better option than dogs, dogs are too dependent and as a student I don’t think this is viable” said Taylor Whittington, a student at American University.  Cats are proven to be more independent than compared to dogs, this has presented an interest in Gen Z and Milenials because of their lifestyles they cannot fit a pet such like a dog that requires more time invested, with cats being flexible to the lifestyles the owners have this has created a trend seen in the past year where local shelters in the area and nationwide have run out of animals to offer for adoption, this has set a competition for shelters and rescue foundations to acquire more animals to satisfy the adoption demands, this has made costumers fly across the country or drive between states to adopt a cat based on their needs of company when back at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Cats and Dog National Adoption Rate (Comparison)&quot; aria-label=&quot;Line Graph&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-jHsMQ&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/jHsMQ/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Cats and Dog National Adoption Rate (Comparison)&quot; aria-label=&quot;Line Graph&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-f3atR&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/f3atR/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparison-of-cats-and-dogs-national-adoption-rates&quot;&gt;Comparison of Cats and Dogs National Adoption Rates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pet industry consists in many branches, from pet food, treats, veterinary care, supplies, insurance, etc, this industry over the past year has reached $99 billion USD, and continues to grow year by year. With an annual rate of growth of 6%, during the past year 21% of pet owners have spent more money on taking care of their pets than in the past years. Inside this industry one of the branches is pet adoptions, when adopting a pet there are related costs to be covered to take care of the animal, whether it is veterinary or insurance related costs to cover, shelters in the country have a down payment required when an individual is willing to adopt a pet whether it is a cat or a dog. This way the shelter can create profit to sustain itself and the upcoming pets that are place inside the shelters with the purpose of being adopted, often these shelters are not government sponsored therefore they charge the future owners a price that does not exceed the regular price of a pet when buying it from a breeder which can range from 500 dollars onwards, adoption charges range between $50-200 USD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leading-pet-product-sales&quot;&gt;Leading Pet Product Sales&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Cats and Dog National Adoption Rate (Comparison)&quot; aria-label=&quot;Line Graph&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-jT4eG&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/jT4eG/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;united-states-pet-industry-sales-by-category&quot;&gt;United States Pet Industry Sales by Category&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Cats and Dog National Adoption Rate (Comparison)&quot; aria-label=&quot;Line Graph&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-31sTl&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/31sTl/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pet industry is currently growing and will continue to grow based on the interest of both adopting or purchasing animals and taking care of their needs. When taking care of their needs there are owners who look for high end products that will guarantee the best health for their pets, this are the factors that push this industry to exponentially grow. When “humanizing” pets, there are more possibilities inside this industry to create markets that satisfy different types of income that pet owners have, this industry has all the space for creativity within the entrepreneurs that offer services and goods for pets, this is why with the evolving times and technology this industry is predicted to grow to $365.62 billion dollars by the year of 2027.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at the past year of 2020, there has been a trend studied on the interest on purchasing or adopting pets, but the trend has set for adoption of pets because pet owners are well aware of the implications buying from breeders can do for the owner and the animal itself. Irresponsible breeding or backyard breeding’s has existed since the beginning, this has created a response from Gen Z and Millennial who are influencing the pet industry and the adoption rates, because they chose to acquire an animal going through the moral implications were the animal is not harm in the process. By adopting pets, owners ensure that the pet does not suffer any consequences from breeding that can result in early death of the animal or possible euthanasia, Debra Duel from the Human Rescue Alliance where their mission is to grow families through adoption, protect animals from harm and provide programs where people and pets can stay together,  stated, “Pets should be a lifetime investment, not something that will keep you company for a   few year, it is your responsibility to give the animal a long and healthy life, this is why I choose adopting, it is a second chance for animals to live their best lives”. Over the past years with comparison of last year, there has been a forecast that pet adoptions will continue to increase which will fuel the industry to grow more, and both local and nationwide shelters have their compromise of handling pets to responsible owners or families while also educating them through programs on how to make the most of the adopted animal and continue to create awareness programs on how breeding is animal cruelty and adopting is the best and most suitable option when wanting to acquire company from an animal.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 14:47:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/coronavirus-pet-adoptions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/spring-2021/spring-2021/coronavirus-pet-adoptions/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
